<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The secret history of the confederacy, &amp;c. discovered in a conference between the French King and his chief officers. To which is added, articles between Luxemburgh, &amp;c. As also expedients proposed for a peace. / Translated out of French.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2339A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51617442</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51617442</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175367</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05780)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175367)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2730:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The secret history of the confederacy, &amp;c. discovered in a conference between the French King and his chief officers. To which is added, articles between Luxemburgh, &amp;c. As also expedients proposed for a peace. / Translated out of French.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 148 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Richard Baldwin, at the Oxford-Arms Inn in Warwick-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A fictional account.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: faded print with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715 --  Fiction --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Foreign relations --  Europe --  Fiction --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:175367:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175367:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175367:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175367:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175367:3"/>
            <p>Licenſed,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June</hi> 5th. 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Edward Cooke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175367:3"/>
            <p>THE SECRET HISTORY OF THE Confederacy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſcovered in a CONFERENCE Between the French King AND HIS CHIEF OFFICERS.</p>
            <p>To which is added, ARTICLES BETWEEN LUXEMBURGH, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS ALSO <hi>Expedients propoſed for a Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> at the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> Inn in <hi>Warwick-lane,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:175367:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175367:4"/>
            <p>SCarce had they given over <hi>talking</hi> at Court of the taking of <hi>Mons,</hi> and of the advantages that <hi>France</hi> would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by ſo important a Conqueſt, which put into her Hands the Key of all the Spaniſh <hi>Netherlands,</hi> but a whiſpering be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be ſpread abroad, that the Council had ſome new deſign in Hand, which promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed great things and would be the occaſion of as great an umbrage, yea greater than that of <hi>Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Whilſt the Generals were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering together, and Monſieur <hi>de Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gh, de Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge, d' Humieres, Boufflers, Vauban</hi> and others of the ſecret Council were paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to and fro; it was not doubted but there was ſome grand Enterprize on foot. The Criticks of the times, and thoſe which made it their buſineſs to foreſee things to come, met alſo by courſes, and did indiſcreetly caſt the Horoſcope of the place threatned with this Thunderbolt, upon which it was ready to fall; making the Innocent bear the burthen of the Guilty, but withall not diſcovering any thing of their real intentions; for <hi>France</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:175367:5"/> is ſo ſubtle in concealing her deſigns, that ſhe would oblige People to believe quite ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing than what ſhe really intends. Nevertheleſs orders were given that all things ſhould be in readineſs. The Roads were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready fill'd with Waggons and Carts loaden with Ammunition and Proviſion, which went to fill the Magazines of <hi>Mons, Phillip-Ville, Maubeuge,</hi> and <hi>Dinant.</hi> There were never ſeen ſo many Bombs and Carcaſſes, gathered together, and ſent in a time when the rigour of the Winter had rendred the Roads unpaſſable. They were not ſatisfied with the great Stores of Corn and Forrage, that all the conquer'd Countries could furniſh them withall, beſides an innumerable number of Proviſions, rais'd in the Enemies Country by way of Contributions, but alſo the Hay and Oats of <hi>Champaign</hi> and the Neighbouring Provinces, had been tranſported in ſo great abundance, that it reduc'd the People of that Country to the laſt extremity; having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived them of their proper ſubſiſtance. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all theſe Prodigious Preparations, to prevent yet the diſorder which might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to a great and numerous Army, if it ſhould once come to want Proviſions, they made uſe of the ſame Artifice as they had done at the Siege of <hi>Mons,</hi> I mean, that the Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aller General found a way how to bring from
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175367:5"/> 
               <hi>Holland</hi> 100000 Crowns worth of Dutch Cheeſe, by the intelligence he had with a Baker at <hi>Gaunt</hi> who knew the ſecret how to get it convey'd: In the affair of <hi>Mons,</hi> ſo great a proviſion was made, that after the reduction of that place, the Army being firſt furniſh't, the reſt was publickly ſold, for fear it ſhould be ſpoil'd; ſo that nothing was ſeen in the Boats and publick Markets but <hi>Holland</hi> Cheeſe.</p>
            <p>So that we may ſay that <hi>France</hi> partly maintains her Armies, upon the ſubſiſtance of her Enemies; and the opportunity ſhe hath by the means of her Gold and Silver, to ſpread Corruption in a Country as fruitful of Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors as <hi>Brabant,</hi> emboldens her, and makes her undertake in the midſt of Winter, the Siege of the ſtrongeſt places in <hi>Europe,</hi> whilſt the Allies, who do not uſe ſo much precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſee themſelves incapacitated for want of <hi>Magazines,</hi> to enter the Campaign before the Month of <hi>June.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is not of Yeſterday that <hi>France</hi> has been a practitioner in this mattter. In the War of 1672. ſhe managed otherwiſe, for then Marquis <hi>de Louvois</hi> found the way, ſome Months before the Declaration of the War, to draw from the Principal Bankers of the City of <hi>Amsterdam</hi> in ready Mony full eight Millions of Silver.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:175367:6"/>
            <p>This Summ and many others privately raiſed in ſeveral other Cities of theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces were advanced, and defray'd a part of the charge of the War, which had like to have overturn'd the State, and to put it upon the brink of ruin.</p>
            <p>But without calling in the time paſt for our aſſiſtance, or diving into things acted in the precedent Wars and Ranſacking, as we ſay, the Aſhes of the Dead, let us diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Living, and bring upon the Stage the Illuſtrious Marqueſs of <hi>Gaſtenaga,</hi> heretofore Governour of the low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</p>
            <p>What has he not done to fill his Coffers?</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> Cavalry has loſt in him one of the beſt Jockeys in all the Countries of <hi>Germany, Liege,</hi> or <hi>Brabant;</hi> and I do not know how they will do after the Campaign, and who ſhall furniſh them ſufficiently with Horſes to remount their Cavalry. For we reckon that he has conveyed into <hi>France,</hi> ſince the Declaration of the War, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of 40000 Horſe, for which he had three Piſtoles <hi>per</hi> Horſe for his pains.</p>
            <p>But now when we unmask the cauſe of ſo many Misfortunes, muſt we not avow, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we will or no, that we know the evil and are not willing to remedy it? ſince we ſee that no exact inquiry has been made into
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175367:6"/> all theſe rotten Members, who betray'd the good Party, and ſold (by the example of <hi>Judas Iſcariot</hi>) their Country, their Wives, and Children; and all that was moſt Sacred and Inviolable in the Government.</p>
            <p>But to return to my matter in Hand: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having ſo furniſhed the <hi>Magazines,</hi> as we have already ſaid, Orders were diſpatched, which were carried in all haſt by Curriers ſent into <hi>Savoy, Germany</hi> and <hi>Catalonia,</hi> to cauſe all the Troops to be upon their March, in order to be in <hi>Flanders</hi> at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Month of <hi>April.</hi> To cover yet better the great Deſign, and to deceive the Enemies by Marches &amp; Countermarches which were caus'd to be made, Monſieur <hi>Boufflers</hi> had orders to go to <hi>Mons</hi> to command in the abſence of Monſieur <hi>Luxenburgh,</hi> who ſtaid at <hi>Paris</hi> to aſſiſt at the laſt Reſolutions of the great Council of War, which was to be held before the opening of the Campaign, where ſeveral obſtacles and difficulties that Monſieur <hi>de Vauban</hi> and <hi>de Megrini</hi> had propoſed in the Execution of this project were to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided. Now it is acknowledged by all, that theſe two Ingineers are beyond all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy not only the beſt of this Age, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that <hi>France</hi> ever had, ſince ſhe was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by Kings, and that we may call them without <hi>Hyperbole,</hi> the Right Hand of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175367:7"/> Conqueſts that the King has made during the whole courſe of his Reign, and greateſt proſperities, if we conſider the Invention, the good Order, the Capacity, and the quick Execution; in which we may ſay that they have not their fellows in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us ſay alſo without <hi>Hyperbole</hi> or Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, that it is a great advantage for an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Man, when he has to do with a Prince who ſpares nothing for the Execution of a deſign; and this doth not a little contribute to acquire him a great Reputation in the World; whereas others that are in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of other Princes find themſelves with all their Ingenuity, bauk'd and ſtopt, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the midſt of their Carreer, when they are upon a great deſign, by the defect and want of means which ſhould contribute the moſt to make them ſucceed.</p>
            <p>But however it be, Monſieur <hi>de Vauban</hi> and <hi>de Megrini</hi> had orders to be at <hi>Verſailles</hi> to aſſiſt at the finiſhing of this deſign. Monſieur <hi>de Megrini</hi> who made his ordinary abode at <hi>Tournay,</hi> of which he was Governour, depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all haſte to place himſelf, where his Majeſties orders had call'd him, and arriv'd, almoſt at the ſame time as Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> did, who had taken Poſt immediately after the taking of <hi>Montmellian.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:175367:7"/>
            <p>All was now ready for the opening of the Council, and all the Generals his Majeſty had pleas'd to call, were arriv'd.</p>
            <p>The number yet was but very ſmall, the King being in what regards his Council and his Secrets, a Prince as circumſpect as ever was; which is the cauſe that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty confides in ſo few perſons, and that he ordinarily admits none but ſuch as are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely reſerv'd; ſo we we may ſay it is one of the principal Wheels upon which his great deſigns, and his good fortune moves; and that he is come to ſo many Conqueſts on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by this means; and if we ſay of Mony that it is the Sinew of War, we may ſay alſo that Silence is the Soul, and that by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence they are both indiſpenſably and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary, ſince they make Armies move and march where they think fit, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them Victorious and Maſters of the moſt Important Forts, of Provinces, and alſo of whole Kingdoms, as we have experienc'd in the laſt Revolution that happen'd in <hi>England,</hi> which we may ſay was the only time that the French King was deceiv'd; for that ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily he has ſo many precautions, and alſo ſo great a number of <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> well paid in all Courts, that he keeps in his Pocket (ſo to ſpeak) the Key of their Counſels and moſt ſecret Reſolutions.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:175367:8"/>
            <p>But we may ſay that the affair of <hi>England</hi> was miraculous; for how elſe could King <hi>William,</hi> encompaſs'd round with French Spies, as he was in ſuch a place as the <hi>Hague,</hi> (where they were ſeen to walk openly in Troops, and with as much confidence and fierceneſs as if they had been in the midſt of <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Paris</hi>) find nevertheleſs means to hide ſo great an undertaking, to carry it on a whole year, and to truſt but two Miniſters of State with it, to wit Penſionary <hi>Fagel</hi> of happy memory, and Monſieur <hi>Dickvelt,</hi> to make all the Preparations, and at laſt to make them appear by the Reduction of three Kingdoms, and to ſave, by an undertaking as bold as ſucceſsfull, <hi>Europe</hi> from Slavery, and that in the ſight of two mighty Kings his Enemies well Arm'd, who ſtood waiting for him without ever ſtirring, treated him with fool-hardineſs, and flatter'd themſelves with hopes, to ſee him ſwallow'd up in his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, with as much ſhame and Confuſion as the unfortunate Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> was?</p>
            <p>Finally, that I may return to my ſubject, the great Council of War, which was to be held at <hi>Verſailles,</hi> being aſſembled, and all the Generals being there preſent, his Majeſty would according to his cuſtom have a particular Conference with each General, and for this reaſon order'd they ſhould enter
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175367:8"/> in order, one after another, into his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> was firſt call'd, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the greateſt Favourite, and him in whom his Majeſty moſt confided, looking upon him as his greateſt ſupport, and him who would maintain at preſent the Honour of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the Glory of <hi>France.</hi> It will not be alltogether foreign to our purpoſe, before we go any farther, to ſpeak a word of the Perſon of this General.</p>
            <p>We will ſay then that Monſieur <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> ſo much made of and ſo much eſteem'd as now he is, ought not to boaſt to be deſcended from the Illuſtrious and ancient Houſe of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> which has given ſo many Emperors to <hi>Germany,</hi> and ſo many Kings to <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia;</hi> neither is he of the poſterity of thoſe titular Dukes of <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> and <hi>Piney,</hi> Princes of <hi>Tingry;</hi> but a Poſthumous Son of <hi>Francis Lord</hi> of <hi>Bouteville,</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Montmoranci,</hi> who was beheaded at <hi>Paris</hi> the 21. of <hi>June,</hi> 1627. for having kill'd in cold Blood in a Duel ſeveral perſons of Quality. This happen'd under the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the Cardinal <hi>Richelieu.</hi> The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Duke of <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> was then but in the Cradle, and the Counteſs of <hi>Bouteville</hi> his Mother, retir'd her ſelf after this diſgrace to one of her Country Houſes, where ſhe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175367:9"/> liv'd a Melancholy life, till ſuch time as her only Son, whom ſhe very tenderly belov'd, arriv'd at the ſeventh year of his age, an age in which it was fit to take him from the Hands of Women, and put him under the care of Governors capable to give him Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſuitable for a Perſon of Quality.</p>
            <p>By this time Madam <hi>de Bouteville</hi> judg'd that the Mothers Houſe was a place very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for the Education of the young Count, and beſides, being not diſſatisfied to find an occaſion to ſhew a part of her Reſentment of the ſhameful Death of her Husband, ſhe reſolv'd to carry her Son to Court, and preſent him to the King.</p>
            <p>She ſet out then for <hi>Paris</hi> without much Equipage, and being arriv'd ſhe went the next day to St. <hi>Germain,</hi> and demanded Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the King, who was then with the Prince and ſome Lords of the Court. They were mightily ſurpriz'd at the arrival of this Lady, who for many years, had not appear'd in the World, and every one ſtrove to find out the reaſon of it, when ſhe enter'd into the Chamber, having her Son in her Hand, whom ſhe carried ſtraight to the King, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Sir, here is the laſt of the <hi>Montmoranci</hi>'s, which I preſent to your Majeſtty to do with as you think fit.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:175367:9"/>
            <p>The King would have reply'd ſomething to her, but Madam <hi>de Bouteville</hi> not deſiring to engage in any further diſcourſe, retir'd after having perform'd her obeiſance and left the young Count in the Kings Chamber.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> who was naturally very generous, was ſo affected at the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this poor Gentleman, that he told the King, that he having been formerly a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good friend of his Fathers, and of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Montmoranci,</hi> he would do him a very great favour to let him bring up this laſt caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away of a Family which had been dear to him; the King conſented, and the Prince carried him home, caus'd him to be inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and brought up with all imaginable care, particularly in the exerciſes of a Gentleman, ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h as Riding the Great Horſe, and Fencing, and as to that, give me leave to tell you what an old Officer brought up from his infancy in the Lord <hi>Bouteville's</hi> Houſe, did aſſure me, that Monſieur <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> was born ſtraight, and of a good ſhape, and that he appear'd ſo to the Eyes of the World, till he was ten years of age, that the Prince, as we may ſay, forcing nature in the Child, did ſo haraſs him in mounting on Horſe back and fencing, before he was ſtrong enough to bear theſe rude Exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſes, that he thereby loſt one full Third of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:175367:10"/>
            <p>In effect, thoſe that have ſeen him undreſs'd know that he is in a manner all Thighs and Leggs,</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, this laſt opinion is ſcarcely believ'd, if we make Reflection upon his hump back, which gives him ſo ridiculous an Air, and which cannot be look'd upon other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than a natural defect; and it is reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to believe he came into the World in this condition, becauſe we certainly ſee by experience, that the exerciſe of Arms contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes rather to regulate and render the Body free, than to cauſe ſuch imperfections.</p>
            <p>Let it be as it will, he has improv'd it well. We may ſay that he is at preſent a Man after the King's own Heart, ſo it is not to be wonder'd at if he leaves to him the Government of his Armies, ſince he has been bold ſeveral times to ſay, <hi>That he thank'd God that he had caus'd him to be born with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pity and compaſſion, to the end he might be more capable of ſerving the King his Maſter, and executing his deſigns:</hi> A ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtian like ſentiment and worthy of Monſieur <hi>de Luxemburgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as to the Hump in his Back, it will not be amiſs to give an account of a thought which he had the day after the Battle of <hi>Fleurns.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:175367:10"/>
            <p>As he receiv'd the Complements of ſucceſs from the Lieutenant Generals, and other Officers of his Army, ſhewing them his Hump, he told them he had there a reſerve of a Body of Forty Thouſand Men, of which his Enemies knew nothing, which would always render him Victorious, thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marking the Artifices which he made uſe of, which without contradiction makes up a good part of the Necromancy, of which he was accuſed, and which he himſelf has be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to Communicate, ſince he has been a Commander, to the other French Generals.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs <hi>de Bouflers,</hi> who was one of his principal Diſciples, did him moſt Honour; for he it is that at preſent ſeems to have profited moſt by the Leſſons of his Maſter.</p>
            <p>So Monſieur <hi>de Luxemburgh</hi> choſe him to be at the Head of this reſerve, of which he ſpoke, and was very careful in all the Battles, to place him ſo well, that he was ſeen running up and down like a Mad-Man, not to ſay fly, upon the leaſt ſignal that he gave him.</p>
            <p>The King ſeeing him come in, turn'd towards him, and ſpoke in theſe Terms, <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> you are the Perſon at this Day in whom <hi>France</hi> places her greateſt hopes; my People look upon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175367:11"/> you as their <hi>Turenne,</hi> and I my ſelf eſteem you as my right Hand; you ſee me en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in an unhappy War, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes my Treaſure, impoveriſhes my Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, ruins the State, and makes me apprehenſive of unhappy Events.</p>
            <p>It is a lingring Fever, which undermines by little and little my Kingdom, and I fear leſt it ſhould in the iſſue become like <hi>Spain,</hi> that is to ſay, a poor and impotent Deſert.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> I thank your Majeſty for having forgot my paſs'd faults, and for honouring me with the preference of the Command of your Armies before the Marſhal <hi>d' Humieres,</hi> much Older and Wiſer than my ſelf.</p>
            <p>I am at the ſame time very much Obliged to the deceaſed Marqueſs of <hi>Louvois</hi> my good Friend, and to the good Madam <hi>de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenon,</hi> who ſollicited my releaſe, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd all their credit with your Majeſty to get me out of the <hi>Baſtile,</hi> where I had been ſhut up, upon the Death of the Count <hi>de Soiſſons,</hi> and ſeveral other ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which I was branded withall: I vow, I did not expect to be received again into your Grace and Favour, your Majeſty ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had ſince t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e War of 1672 a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar averſion to my P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſon.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:175367:11"/>
            <p>But on the other ſide, I am glad to ſee that my Enemies have for their part ſhame and trouble by the Triumph of my Innocence, after having imploy'd all their power to ruin me. I ſhall remember all my Life time the reverend Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> and the jealous Madam <hi>de Monteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan,</hi> who have been the principal actors of this Tragedy, and if it is natural to keep reſentment, I will reſerve to my ſelf a favourable occaſion to let them know that I have not been either a Necroman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, nor Madam <hi>Brinvilliers</hi> Diſciple.</p>
            <p>But, anſwer'd his Majeſty, Let us not talk of paſs'd Quarrels; altho' what is ſaid of you ſhould be true, and alſo that you had a familiar Spirit to win Battles, to gain the Love of the Ladies, and to pleaſe me, I will in acknowledgment of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices that you have done me in the Wars of <hi>Holland,</hi> and that you may do me in the preſent War, order the Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to burn the Informations and the Tryal, and to forbid any upon pain of Death throughout my whole Kingdom to talk directly or indirectly of it.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwered <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> I moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly thank your Majeſty for the care that you will take of my reputation, and I do engage upon my word, that in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175367:12"/> of ſo great a Favour, I will do for my part, all that lies in my power, to ruin your Enemies, and advance your Conqueſts.</p>
            <p>You know, anſwer'd his Majeſty, That the firſt Campaign, which was that of 1689. I gave the Command of my Army to the Marſhal <hi>d' Humieres,</hi> and that this Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, who is a good Man, did really do me good ſervice.</p>
            <p>For it was him that I ſent Ambaſſador to the Court of <hi>England,</hi> immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Death of King <hi>Charles,</hi> and he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted my Orders very punctually. For King <hi>James,</hi> who came to be Crown'd King of three Kingdoms, received him with open Arms, and very generouſly accepted all the offers of Alliance and Friendſhip that <hi>Humieres</hi> made him on my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half.</p>
            <p>But this unfortunate Prince afterwards not having followed my Orders, found himſelf all of a ſudden overwhelm'd with great troubles, and has engag'd me in a War which has Arm'd all <hi>Europe</hi> againſt me.</p>
            <p>But to come to my purpoſe: Having then choſe him to Command in <hi>Flanders</hi> againſt Prince <hi>Waldeck,</hi> a General of good Conduct, and well inſtructed in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175367:12"/> what concern'd the Order that an Army in her Marches and Incampments ought to be kept in; but on the other hand ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unlucky to hazard a Battle; I remark'd that in this firſt year, the Marſhal <hi>d' Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mieres</hi> ſuffer'd himſelf to be Coop'd up, as we ſay, by Prince <hi>Waldeck,</hi> and that he had during the whole Campaign the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage.</p>
            <p>I remember alſo very well the Battle of <hi>Walcourt,</hi> which was on the Great St. <hi>Louis</hi> day, Patron and Protector of my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, where all my Houſe-hold was Cut in pieces; but I pardon him with all my heart, becauſe he did it with a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and belief of doing me Service that day. The little Genius of <hi>d' Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eres</hi> was not only the cauſe of this check; but we may alſo ſay that he favour'd, by the little motion he made, the Enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, who took Three good Cities from me that year.</p>
            <p>The deceaſed Marqueſs <hi>de Louvois,</hi> whom I now very much lament, foretold it me; the good Man was a very good Phyſiognomiſt, and as he knew his People extremely well, ſo he was obſerved not to be miſtaken in the choice he made of Perſons of merit to fill the vacant places, which has been the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175367:13"/> cauſe, that during my Reign, I have always had the choiceſt Perſons.</p>
            <p>It was he that preſented Monſieur <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinat</hi> to me, to Command in <hi>Italy,</hi> being a Man, he ſaid, who had experience, and the good Fortune to have paſs'd through all the inferiour degrees in the War, having been formerly a common Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier.</p>
            <p>I was alſo willing to imploy the Duke of <hi>Duras</hi> to Command in <hi>Germany;</hi> but <hi>Louvois</hi> advis'd me rather to ſend the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal <hi>de Lorge</hi> his Brother, as a Man who had more of Softneſs and execution, which agrees better with the natural ſlowneſs of the <hi>Germans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I had alſo made choice of Monſieur <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zun</hi> for <hi>Ireland,</hi> at the Sollicitation of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damoiſelle <hi>de Monpenſier</hi> my Couſin, but the poor Man is no more what he was, and the affairs of that Kingdom were quite changed after the loſs of the Battle of the <hi>Boyn,</hi> where he commanded joyntly with King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Louvois</hi> advis'd me to call him back as ſoon as poſſibly, and to ſend the brave St. <hi>Ruth</hi> of happy memory, whom I much lament, becauſe he was the Man that Purg'd my Kingdom of the Huguenot He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:175367:13"/>
            <p>He was naturally haſty, but brave as his Sword.</p>
            <p>Be it as it will, I found him very ſervicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to me, and if he had not been unfortuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely kill'd by a Cannon Bullet, I am perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the War would have laſted ſtill in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> would not have come off ſo cheap in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is alſo the deceaſed Marquis of <hi>Louvois</hi> who preſented <hi>Tourville</hi> to me to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand my Fleet, as an Admiral of a gallant Perſon; And I vow that I have had till this very time a great deal of trouble to ſtop the Torrent of his Courage. He talks to me in all my undertakings of nothing but giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Battle to the Enemy. Hitherto I have always hindred him, becauſe I was not altogether ſatisfied with the Engagement of 1690. where the <hi>Hollanders</hi> alone with 20. or 22. Men of War, dar'd to attack him at the head of my Fleet, which was compoſed of more than 80. great Ships, whilſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> contented themſelves to be Spectators; and that which cauſed aſtoniſhment, was, that after a Fight of more than Six hours, not one of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Ships was taken, having retreated after the Fight in very good order, tho' in truth diſabled and unmaſted. So the laſt Expedition, I order'd him to ſhun all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:175367:14"/> Engageing, and when the Enemies ſhould be on the one ſide, to go on the other; which he obſerv'd very well</p>
            <p>'Tis alſo from the ſame hand that the Marquiſs <hi>de Bouflers</hi> was preſented to me, tho' in truth Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> alſo contributed, for ſhe wearied me Night and Day, and I never ſaw her but ſhe ſpoke to me of him.</p>
            <p>But I have not been deceiv'd in him.</p>
            <p>He is one of the braveſt Officers that I have at this Day in my Armies, and from whom I reap the greateſt benefit, by the Contributions, which he takes care to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together, and to make my Enemies pay in ready mony, which makes a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Sum, deſign'd to buy Horſes to re-mount my Cavalry.</p>
            <p>For his pains, I have lately made him Captain of my Guards, beſides ſeveral other good Offices which he poſſeſſes; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more I have reſerv'd a Marſhals Staff for him, if the War laſt two Campaigns more.</p>
            <p>'Tis <hi>Louvois</hi> alſo who preſented to me Monſieur <hi>Amelott</hi> (formerly my Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor at <hi>Venice</hi>) to go and reſide with the Laudable <hi>Swiſs Cantons</hi> during this War.</p>
            <p>I have been deceiv'd in him no more than in Monſieur <hi>Bouflers,</hi> for if this knows
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:175367:14"/> how to uſe a Piſtol, and is able in the handling of a Sword, the other is no leſs in that of the Pen. It is alſo to his good conduct that I attribute all the good intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, which reigns at preſent amongſt my Couſins the <hi>Suiſſers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let him but make a Speech with Words well plac'd, back'd with a good Purſe of my <hi>Louiſſes,</hi> diſtributed under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand and behind the Curtain, I obtain im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately all I would have. They grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me the laſt Campaign the raiſing of ten thouſand Men of new Troops.</p>
            <p>I hope they will grant me this Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign at leaſt fifteen thouſand to fill up the number of the forty thouſand that I have in my ſervice, with whom I am very well ſatisfied, for they are the beſt Foot of my Army.</p>
            <p>I ought not to forget to ſpeak one word by the way of their General <hi>Stouppa,</hi> with whom I am very well contented, who ſeems to have chang'd his Country in changing his Religion, that is to ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a good French-Man. He takes ſo ſtrongly to Heart my intereſts, that we ſee him boldly march at the Head of the <hi>Swiſſer</hi>'s Troops, every where, and in all places, laughing at certain old and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Treaties, which ſay that the <hi>Swiſſers</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:175367:15"/> that are in my Service, ſhall not act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Emperour and his Allies. 'Tis <hi>Louvois</hi> alſo who preſented to me the Count of <hi>Bethune</hi> that I lately ſent to the King of <hi>Sweedland</hi> to feel the pulſe of that Prince, and to ſee if there was no way to engage him to a Rupture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bidall</hi> writ to me that he could no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger retain his Reſentment, and that the Engliſh and Dutch Capers might make him become one <hi>of the French Intereſt.</hi> I have given order to the Count <hi>de Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hune</hi> to ſay at his arrival at <hi>Stockholme,</hi> That he was arriv'd by chance, and that a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt had caſt him there, that he may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal ſo much the better his Negotiation. I hear, thanks to God, that he is happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arriv'd. I have alſo in <hi>Holland</hi> one of the Diſciples of <hi>Bethune,</hi> which doth me very good ſervice, and who has well ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Count <hi>d' Avaux.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Count <hi>de Bethune</hi> had conſiderable Summs to pay to Madam <hi>Morean's</hi> Father a rich Merchant at <hi>Paris,</hi> but finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf disabl'd to ſerve him, he engag'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to obtain of the King of <hi>Poland</hi> (by my recommendation) Letters of credit for Monſieur <hi>Moreau</hi> her Husband, and that by this means he might, as we ſay, kill two Birds with one Stone, and be as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:175367:15"/> 
               <hi>Janus</hi> with two Faces, in calling himſelf Envoy of the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in effect the place of the Count <hi>d' Avaux</hi> in his abſence. I am very well ſatisfied with him, and I eſteem him as one of my beſt Correſpondents in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Count <hi>de Bethune</hi> ſhall have made the firſt motion to the Northern Princes, I have then the Count <hi>d' Avaux,</hi> and <hi>Bonrepos,</hi> ready to ſet ſail for that Coaſt, to go and finiſh what <hi>Bethune</hi> ſhall have begun.</p>
            <p>I have made choice of theſe two Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters <hi>d' Avaux</hi> for <hi>Sweedland,</hi> and <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repos</hi> for <hi>Denmark,</hi> becauſe truly I judg them moſt proper to bring thoſe two Crowns to a Mediation; their manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment accompanied with ſome Millions may buy a peace, or at leaſt ſet a good ſtep towards it. <hi>D' Avaux</hi> has done me great Services in <hi>Holland,</hi> and knows the Republican Spirit to the bottom. St. <hi>Didier</hi> his Secretary, and whom I call his <hi>Achates,</hi> has orders to follow him, becauſe he underſtands admirably well to draw up a Memorial proper to perſuade, and bring them into a Snare.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sieur de Rebenack</hi> was alſo preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me by Monſieur <hi>Louvois,</hi> and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:175367:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:175367:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:175367:17"/> have I forgot what he told me in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending him to me.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid he, here is the moſt active of your Subjects, and from whom your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty may receive great Services, if you ſend him Ambaſſadour to the Northern Crowns; which I did accordingly, and truly he did me very good ſervice at the Court of the deceaſed Elector of <hi>Brande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I knew by his Intreagues all that paſs'd there. The Kings of <hi>Sweedland</hi> and <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> did nothing but what I came to the knowledg of, by his means; ſo that I did not trouble my ſelf to have on that ſide any other Spy, nor correſpondence but his. Since calling him home, I ſent <hi>Bidal</hi> in his place, and it is he alſo actually takes care of my intelligence in thoſe Countries.</p>
            <p>But anſwer'd <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> I have heard that your Majeſty has ſent <hi>Rebenack</hi> lately into <hi>Italy,</hi> to endeavour to bring the Princes of thoſe parts to imbrace your ſide, or at leaſt a good Neutrality. It is true, ſaid his Majeſty, and (I wiſh) he may croſs the deſigns of the <hi>Germans,</hi> and perſuade the Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> not to grant them Winter Quarters.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:175367:17"/>
            <p>He has orders to go to all thoſe Courts, by what I can underſtand his Negotiation will not be altogether in vain, having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready put many of thoſe Princes into a wavering condition. The great Duke of <hi>Tuſcany</hi> and the Republick of <hi>Genoua</hi> have promis'd him, and I hope the reſt will follow.</p>
            <p>Sir, reply'd <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> muſt he not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo take a turn to <hi>Rome</hi> to kiſs the Slipper of Innocent the 12th. on the behalf of your Majeſty? for by what I can learn that good Father has more of a French Heart than <hi>Alexander</hi> the 8th. and <hi>Innocent</hi> the 11th. his Predeceſſors. Without doubt, anſwer'd his Majeſty, for the Holy Father granted me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all I ask'd of him, whereas the others refus'd me every thing. He has already granted the greateſt part of the neceſſary Bulls, to the Biſhops of my Kingdom, and promis'd to the Count <hi>d' Eſtree</hi> to endeavour with all forwardneſs to procure a peace to Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>Now I think on't Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> how does your Majeſty like the Baron <hi>de Chateauneuf,</hi> whom I took the liberty to preſent to be your Ambaſſadour at <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Very well, ſays his majeſty, he is a gown Man, &amp; come out of my Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:175367:18"/> where he paſs'd for an able Man in buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and I wanted ſuch a Man as him; for by what I can learn he is an artiſt in perſuading the Grand Signior. Beſides, the beſt of it is that he is very well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd by the Grand Viſir, who has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd him to hearken to no peace this Campaign, but even that, not without two hundred thouſand Crowns which he was oblig'd to pay him.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> Mony at this Day affords great help to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; and if it ſhould come once to fail I do not know how all would go. That puts me in mind of what the Hiſtory of our Kings report of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, who was Sirnam'd the Wiſe that he without going out of his Cloſet, had always the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage over the Engliſh, and obtain'd all his deſigns.</p>
            <p>After his Death he was called rich, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe at his Death he left 17 Millions of Crowns, which was a prodigious Sum at that time. I much doubt if your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty had reign'd in that time, whether you would have ſucceeded in all your En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes with ſo ſmall a Sum; ſince we ſee that you have a great deal of trouble to do it with the three hundred Millions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Livers that you draw from your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:175367:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> ſays his Mayjeſty, a Prince which is abſolute over his People, and who is by conſequence Maſter of their Eſtates, has Mines of Gold and Silver which never conſume; theſe Springs ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver dry up, and are infinitely richer and more abounding than thoſe of <hi>Mexico</hi> and <hi>Peru;</hi> and we ſee in our Days that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> that furniſhes (as we may ſay) all other Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> with all the Riches they have, and all the Gold and Silver which rules in the trade of each People and each Nation, is nevertheleſs the leaſt partaker of it, and has the moſt occaſion for it.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> if your predeceſſours <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth and <hi>Louis</hi> the Thirteenth had had the Deſpotick and Arbitrary Power, as your Majeſty has at this Day, eſpecially <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, who was a ſtirring Prince and full of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity; what could they not have done?</p>
            <p>The true art to reign, ſays his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, was unknown to them, and they knew not how to make any profit of the leſſons of <hi>Machiavel,</hi> and of the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable <hi>Richelieu</hi> and <hi>Mazarine,</hi> who have been the only perſons that have taught it; ſo that I do not ſee of all my Anceſtors why <hi>Louis</hi> the Eleventh ſhould make ſo
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:175367:19"/> much uſe of that Principle which was attributed to him, and which has been ſince call'd the Maxim of <hi>Louis</hi> the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, <hi>qui neſcit diſſimulare, neſcit regnare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that knows not how to diſſemble, knows not how to Reign.</p>
            <p>As to the matter of Mony, ſays <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> how does your Majeſty like <hi>Pont-Chartrain,</hi> that the deceaſed Monſieur <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> recommended to you before his Death, as a Man very proper to manage your Treaſury?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pontchartrain,</hi> anſwer'd his Majeſty, doth me good ſervice in the preſent conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, and I know not how all would go if I had him not. When I find my ſelf ſhort of Mony, which often happens by reaſon of the preſſing neceſſities of the War, I need only ſay to him, I have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for ſo many Millions; as he is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ingenious and one of the beſt Partizans that has ever been in <hi>France,</hi> he immediately invents ſome new Impoſt upon the People, or ſome new Tax upon thoſe which are po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt of places.</p>
            <p>Nor is this all, for he is expert to find out means, how to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e it preſently in ready Mony.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgh,</hi> I believe your Majeſty very much laments th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s you
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:175367:19"/> had by the deceaſed Mr. <hi>Colbert,</hi> which was an underſtanding Man, if ever there was any in the management of your Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury.</p>
            <p>He was too much hated by the People, ſays his Majeſty; they began to call him Thief, they accus'd him of having ruin'd <hi>France,</hi> and made it a general Hoſpital; and yet he never did any thing but by my order, and acquainting me with all he did. Let it be as it will, he has been the Inſtrument of a great many things, of which I ſhould never have thought of, had not he perſwaded me unto them.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, for the quieting of my People, I am glad that his death has taken this Obſtacle out of their way that was a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to them; and as we love Novelties, we always flatter our ſelves, that the laſt comer will be better than the former; all the World conceiv'd great hopes upon the Arrival of <hi>Pontchartrain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> I think that <hi>Colbert</hi> had gather'd together great Riches, which he poſſeſs'd as his own, and all his Children became very great.</p>
            <p>It is true, ſays his Majeſty, but after his Death the Water came to it's Spring, and I caus'd full and good Reſtitution to be made: I made uſe of a ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:175367:20"/> to drain them, which brought ſome Millions into my Coffers.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> let us let all thoſe matters alone which do not concern the War; your Majeſty has no time to loſe, the matter in hand is now to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent your Enemies, and be early in the Field, ſo that it's time to take a firm and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid reſolution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> you have reaſon, ſays his Majeſty, and it is alſo for that purpoſe I caus'd you to come hither, together with my other Generals, to hear you one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to have a private conference about what I ought to undertake.</p>
            <p>But as you are one of thoſe in whom I have moſt confidence; and that on the other ſide my deſign is to make <hi>Flanders</hi> the principal Theatre of the War, where I pretend that my great deſigns ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, I will impart every thing to you with an open heart. You are a Man of experience, and the Wars of Seventy Two has given you a particular know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of that Country. I lament extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the poor Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> he alſo knew perfectly the Genius and Intereſts of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Schombergh</hi> would have alſo been of great uſe to me if his infatuation to Religion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:175367:20"/> had not made him periſh miſerably in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Poor <hi>Turenne,</hi> the Flower of all my Generals, <hi>hac Coelum itur via,</hi> merited the ſame Honours, that the Gods formerly gave to great <hi>Hercules</hi> in memory of his Toils, I mean Immortality.</p>
            <p>Be it as it will, I ſhall never forget the good ſervice he did me in <hi>Germany,</hi> and of ſo many brave Captains, you are the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one that is left me; ſo I deſire you not to expoſe your ſelf too much, and to take as much care of your dear Perſon as my Armies. For if I ſhould come to loſe you, I ſhould not know who to give the Command to, having for the moſt part none but Lieutenant Generals, more fit to Command a party of Incendiaries, than an Army ſo conſiderable as that in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> coming every Campaign to Command himſelf, would deſire no better than to have to do with a Novice; nor the fiery Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> who alſo commands with him.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Princes fly round about my Army as a Bird of Prey about a Swallow, and ſeek nothing elſe, but to make me loſe a Battle to make way for them into <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> here is now a trick
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:175367:21"/> of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> which puts me in deſpair. He is not contented to mount the Throne of <hi>England</hi> after poor King <hi>James</hi> his Father-in-Law, and my Ally, was retired to my Court; but he does yet worſe in reſpect to me, for he has found out a means to drive me out of the Low-Countries, endeavouring to deprive the <hi>Dauphin</hi> my Son of the Provinces fallen to his Mother my Wife the moſt Chriſtian Queen, by the deceaſe of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> her Mother, of Prince <hi>Don Balthazar</hi> her Brother, and of the Catholick King <hi>Philip</hi> the Fourth, her Father. The Stratagem that he has made uſe of is, he has brought the King of <hi>Spain, Charles</hi> the Second, to make a gift <hi>ad vitam</hi> of the Spaniſh <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands</hi> to the Elector of <hi>Bavaria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They made a ſhew ſome years ago to have play'd this trick; but I made ſuch ſtrong Proteſtations, and threatnings to come into <hi>Flanders</hi> with a great Army, without having any regard to the Truce, that they thought fit for the Peace of thoſe Provinces, and the repoſe of <hi>Europe</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the matter to another time.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> all this good ſucceſs we owe to the taking of <hi>Mons,</hi> and the good Correſpondence that the good Marquis <hi>de Gastanaga</hi> had kept with us,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:175367:21"/> which was thereby diſcover'd.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> ſeeing the Spaniſh <hi>Netherlands</hi> were ſold at a great price by the covetouſneſs of the Governours, reſolv'd to play a Maſterpiece in cauſing it to be put into better hands, who would make it their glory to preſerve it.</p>
            <p>But, ſays his Majeſty, can that be done without injuſtice, and can they diſpute with my Son the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> as they would have diſputed with me in the time of the Wars of <hi>Paris,</hi> that the moſt Chriſtian Queen <hi>Maria Tiereſia,</hi> formerly Infanta of <hi>Spai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and immediaely after the <hi>Pirenaean</hi> Peace became my Wife, was brought to Bed of a Prince at <hi>Fountain Bleau,</hi> on All <hi>Saints</hi> day, the firſt of <hi>November,</hi> a little before Noon in the year 1661.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> the <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins</hi> Birth is not the thing in Queſtion; no Body doubts but he is truly your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties and the Queen <hi>Maria Tiereſia's</hi> Son. We are well ſatisfied with the fruitfulneſs of that Princeſs.</p>
            <p>And as to what properly concerns your Majeſties Perſon, you have, thanks to God, furniſh'd us with Patterns, taken from the Originals of the Lad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>de Fontanges, la Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liere,</hi> and <hi>la Mourteſpan,</hi> who have l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ft enough of Illuſtrious young <hi>Sprigs,</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:175367:22"/> the Duke <hi>de Main,</hi> Madam the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Conti,</hi> and <hi>Madamoiſelle de Blois</hi> now Dutcheſs of <hi>Charters.</hi> As for Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> who ſucceeded them, I dare not ſpeak of, becauſe I am perſwaded it is a Soil where the beſt Seeds-men ſeem to me to looſe their time and trouble, unleſs God would make her a <hi>Sarah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to <hi>Madamoiſelle de Blois,</hi> I muſt tell your Majeſty by the way, that they talk very much of her Marriage with Monſieur the Duke <hi>de Charters,</hi> in Foreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and Principally in <hi>Holland,</hi> where they Criticize even upon the leaſt Actions of Kings and Princes.</p>
            <p>All the World take upon them here to talk of Politicks, nay even the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p>They ſay that your Majeſty has by this Marriage, and by that of the Princeſs <hi>de Conti,</hi> unworthily and without diſtinction, mixt the pure with the impure, and that if this ſhould continue, there would not remain in <hi>France</hi> one drop of the Noble Blood of your Great Grandfathers, and that we ſhould ſee no other in the Royal Family, but the Children of <hi>la Valliere,</hi> and <hi>la Monteſpan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to come to my matter in Hand, that which is the Queſtion is, that the Allies
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:175367:22"/> pretend the renunciation your Majeſty made at the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Peace has forfeited you your Right and Pretenſions, which you might have had to the Succeſſion we were ſpeaking of.</p>
            <p>But, ſays his Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſty, it was not in my power to diſpoſe of thoſe Rights, and to renounce them to the prejudice of my Son; according to all Laws, the Fathers have no right to alienate the Eſtates of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren whilſt they are Minors, and when theſe Eſtates are Maternal.</p>
            <p>But, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> the Marriage was only concluded upon this condition; ſo that the renunciation your Majeſty made upon all the preſent and future Right that you might have upon <hi>Spain,</hi> or upon the depending States, was conſider'd as the Ground of Marriage, without which the Miniſters of <hi>Spain</hi> would have been guilty of a great deal of Folly on their ſide, to have conſented to an Ally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance which would have produc'd n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w cauſes of Wars and Diviſions, inſtead of a Firm and Stable Peace, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h was their chief deſign.</p>
            <p>I add to all theſe proofs, that the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of the Oath that your Majeſty was obliged to take in ſwearing ſolemnly upon the Holy Evangeliſts, that you
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:175367:23"/> would keep your Royal World that you then gave, was as the Seal of all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, of the engagements, and of the good Faith of your Majeſty.</p>
            <p>In your opinion, ſays the King, I am then very ill grounded in my pretenſions, and I have no right according to the Civil Law.</p>
            <p>No, without doubt, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> but a hundred thouſand Men, a hundred pieces of Cannon, and a hundred Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions will make the Ballance incline much more to your ſide.</p>
            <p>It was a cuſtom to repreſent Juſtice blindfolded, holding a Balance in one Hand; but if the other had not been arm'd with a Sword, and had a Lion plac'd by her ſide, which is the badge of Force and Might, ſhe would have been but a ridiculous Maygame, expos'd to the violence and raſhneſs of Men. So we may ſay, he that has the power in his Hand is the Maſter of Juſtice, and whether ſhe will or no, muſt of neceſſity betake her ſelf to his ſide, and fight under his Standards againſt the weakeſt, and this is your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Right. But, ſays his Majeſty, ſince things are in this condition, and that I ſee my ſelf Maſter of Force and of Juſtice, ſhall I not do well to puſh my good fortune to the end, and to render my ſelf, by my
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:175367:23"/> Armies always victorious and triumphant over all the States which ſhall be at my diſcretion and ſerve for my conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, having placed my ſelf ſafe from the oppoſition of mine Enemies? Very well, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> there is no other obſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle which is capable to ſtop your Majeſty but the Faith of Treaties. But that is another Goſpel for your Majeſty for which you care but very little. We ſay of King <hi>John</hi> the Firſt, one of your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors deſcended from the firſt Branch of <hi>Valois,</hi> that that Prince was ſo great an obſerver of his Word, that they gave him the Title of Good. He was accuſtomed to ſay, that when Fidelity and good Faith ſhould be baniſhed the World, they ought to be found in the perſon of a Prince.</p>
            <p>This Prince, anſwer'd his Majeſty, did not know <hi>Machiavel;</hi> and you ſhould have added at the ſame time that he was very unhappy during his Reign; and I do not doubt but his too great Goodneſs was in part the cauſe of his Misfortunes.</p>
            <p>For having loſt the Battle of <hi>Poictiers</hi> againſt the Engliſh, who were commanded by the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> a great Captain, the King was taken and carried Priſoner to <hi>London,</hi> from whence he came not out, but by the treaty of <hi>Bretigny,</hi> by which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:175367:24"/> he quitted the Sovereignty of ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces in <hi>France</hi> in f vour of the King of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all theſe faults of <hi>John</hi> the Firſt were gloriouſly repaired by <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth his Succeſſor, who acquir'd to him ſelf the name of Wife.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> ſince your Majeſty Laughs ſo at the good Faith of Treaties, which other Princes look upon as Inviolable and adore as an Idol, I am not ſurpriz'd that you have heap'd up Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt upon Conqueſt.</p>
            <p>There is never a little Prince in the World but may be in a condition to make himſelf great by this means, and at laſt become the terror of his Enemies; but it is not to be wiſhed that ſuch a like diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhould happen, for if every Soveraign ſhould do the like, we ſhould ſee a great number of Scepters overthrown to the ground become the Prey of the ſtrongeſt.</p>
            <p>But, ſays his Majeſty, ſince it is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to make ones ſelf great, what's the reaſon that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is Mounted even in our Days upon the Throne of his Father-in-Law? Is not that an Uſurpation?</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> that is not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, Hiſtories are full of ſuch like inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:175367:24"/> and we ſee that <hi>Childerick</hi> the Third, laſt King of the firſt Race was Dethron'd by <hi>Pepin</hi> the Short, who before was but Mayor of the Palace, which was a place almoſt like that of Grand <hi>Viſirs;</hi> and his depoſing was alſo done by the Aſſembly of the States, after the <hi>Pope</hi> had declar'd that the <hi>French</hi> were diſpens'd with from owning that Prince.</p>
            <p>So that the poor Dethroned <hi>Childerick</hi> had no other part to take, but to ſhave himſelf, and put himſelf into a Monaſtery. And as this diſgrace happen'd to him by reaſons of State, which would be too long to report, ſo the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is not mounted upon the Throne but by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the People which call'd him to it. And the Parliament it ſelf which being in <hi>England</hi> very near to what the States were formerly in <hi>France,</hi> Crown'd him and confirm'd him; <hi>nemine contradicente;</hi> ſo the coming of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to the Crown ought to be call'd an <hi>Acceptance</hi> and not an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to this ſenſe, ſays his M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, you are then of opinion that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is well grounded, and that the poor King <hi>James</hi> has no ſhorter Courſe to take in the midſt of his diſgraces than to imitate <hi>Childeric;</hi> that is to ſay, to make a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:175367:25"/> rennuciation of the Crown, ſhave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and ſo put himſelf into a Convent.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> I abuſe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, the liberty your Majeſty allows me, ſpeaking open hearted my Mind, and what I think of the misfortune of this Prince. But as in the beginning of this Conference your Majeſty was pleaſed to ſay you put a great deal of Confidence in me, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you alſo to give me leave to abſtain from the language of certain Paraſites who applaud your Majeſty in every thing.</p>
            <p>No, <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> ſays his Majeſty, you do me a kindneſs to tell me the things as you think t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em; that does not ſurpriſe me, becauſe I have always given you more liberty to ſpeak your thoughts than any of my Courtiers and Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> ſince your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty gives me leave to ſpeak what I think of King <hi>James</hi> and of the War which has been kindled in <hi>Europe,</hi> upon his occaſion; I do not now ſpeak of a ſecret itching deſire that your Majeſty had from your Cradle to ſurpaſs your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, in enlarging your Dominions, and puſhing on you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Conqueſts beyond the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the <hi>Sambre,</hi> and <hi>Meuſe;</hi> I ſpeak
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:175367:25"/> not neither of the Rights of the deceaſed Queen: I paſs alſo in ſilence the Right of dependance, which is an old quarrel that your Majeſty has with the Emperour, and the Princes of the Empire: I will hold my Tongue alſo as to what regards that ſecret enmity which has reign'd in all Ages, between the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and that of <hi>Bourbon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I will come forthwith to matter of fact, and that which is now before us is, that your Majeſty did procure to your ſelf a War in the year, 1689. which is now four years agoe, and that upon the occaſion, 1ſt. Of the Univerſal Monarchy, 2dly. Becauſe of <hi>Pope Innocent</hi> the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, who oppos'd himſelf to all your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns. 3dly. Upon occaſion of the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal de Furſtembergh.</hi> 4thly. To hinder the ruin of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire. 5thly. To re-inſtall King <hi>James</hi> in his Throne: Of all theſe Articles I will chuſe but one, and with your Majeſties permiſſion will inſiſt upon the laſt, which is in my Opinion the moſt important, and which I conſider as an invincible obſtacle to a glorious Peace, which ought to be the end of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Arms and Enterprizes. I ſay then, that your Majeſty finds your ſelf at this day in a great confuſion, by the weight
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:175367:26"/> of the War which you are obliged to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, which is one of the bloodieſt, the moſt pernicious, and the moſt burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome that <hi>France</hi> ever had. And really to run through all the Reigns that have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded this, we do not ſee that <hi>Charles</hi> the Seventh, <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, <hi>Charles</hi> the Eighth, <hi>Charlemain,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, no more than <hi>Louis</hi> the Thirteenth, have had ſo many Enemies at one time upon their Hands.</p>
            <p>But that which ſurprizes me the moſt, and which I look upon as a Miracle, is, that in the midſt of ſo many Enemies your Majeſty equally enjoys your ſelf, and gives your Orders every where with as much tranquility as if you were in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Peace. Things being in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition I have but one thing to know of your Majeſty, which I deſire you to truſt me with; after which I will ingage my ſelf to lay down a way which ſhall infallibly conduct you to a general peace in leſs than two Campaigns.</p>
            <p>I have already told you, <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> ſays his Majeſty, that I put full confidence in you, and that I have choſen you as one of my beſt Counſellors in the condition I find my ſelf; becauſe really I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark'd, that my Affairs have put on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:175367:26"/> Face, &amp; run quite in another Channel from the very moment you took the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of my Army; and I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my Enemies fear you more than my other Generals, or whether the Familiar Spirit, as is ſaid, that you have to win Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, makes you Bolder and more undaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Be it as it will, the Battle of <hi>Fleu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> which you won me, has been a great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to me: It has put my tottering Affairs into a good condition; and if any other but you had had the diſpoſal of it, I ſhould have run a great hazard of loſing it, ſince that fifty thouſand Men of my beſt Troops had a great deal of trouble to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat twenty four thouſand which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd the Enemies Army. I add alſo this circumſtance, that the Victory being a long time Ballanc'd by the great reſiſtance which the Enemies Foot made, and which you did not expect, you were alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to encourage my Troops, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd to charge again the fourth time, and pulling off your Hat deſir'd the Officers to put themſelves in mind of the honour of <hi>France,</hi> and of the glory of their Prince; which ſo ſtrongly animated them, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Charge they oblig'd the Victory to declare it ſelf for my Arms. I believe, if poor <hi>d' Humieres</hi> had been there to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:175367:27"/> command as he was the Campaign before, the good Man would have been in a great deal of trouble. But I much doubt, <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emburgh,</hi> if the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had been at the Head of that Army, whether you would have come off ſo cheap as you did with Prince <hi>Waldeck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> when I ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand againſt the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> I will content my ſelf to play the cunning part; but when Prince <hi>Waldeck</hi> ſhall Command, I pretend to go eat his Bread, and to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp in his Country, and to lead him up and down where I pleaſe; the reaſon of it is, that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is ſtirring and ſpares not his own Perſon, preſenting himſelf every where in a Battle, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning danger, enjoying himſelf, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Orders without confuſion.</p>
            <p>But, ſays his Majeſty, How did you do at the buſineſs of <hi>Leuſſe?</hi> for he was at the Head of that Army all the Campaign.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> I took care not to attack his Army at that time, but I juſt took the occaſion of his departure, and with difficulty came to underſtand by Six of my beſt Spies, that he was Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at <hi>Breda,</hi> when I made the Horſe march. To deceive the Enemies by a Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem pleaſant enough, I took with me
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:175367:27"/> Meſſieurs the Dukes <hi>de Charters</hi> and <hi>du Main,</hi> and we went all three to <hi>Tournay</hi> with a deſign to ſee there a Play. We ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd there about Six of the Clock in the Afternoon, it was juſt the Eve of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which was to paſs the next day about 8 or 9 of the Clock in the Morning, as we had contriv'd.</p>
            <p>The Spies of Prince <hi>Waldeck,</hi> with which he was not the beſt provided, did not fail to give him an account we were at the Play, as it was true; but I had before given Orders to the <hi>Sieur de Roze,</hi> to <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieurs</hi> the Counts <hi>d' Auvergne</hi> and <hi>de Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy,</hi> countenanced by the Prince <hi>de Soubiſe,</hi> and the Marqueſs <hi>de Congis,</hi> to advance very ſlowly with about Sixty or Eighty Squadrons divided into ſeveral parties.</p>
            <p>The Comedy which they Play'd, was <hi>The Phyſician in Spight of himſelf;</hi> which being ended, one of the Players invited the Company the next day to another, call'd <hi>The Citizen turn'd Gentleman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Drawing near Monſieur the Duke <hi>du Maine,</hi> I whiſper'd him ſoftly in the Ear, by my faith we ſhall have another Comedy to morrow, not to ſay Tragedy, for it ſeems to me as if it would not be very bloody.</p>
            <p>That being done, we got on Horſeback
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:175367:28"/> about Nine of the Clock, and return'd by the obſcurity of the Night near to your Majeſties Troops. And by good Fortune there aroſe a thick Fog, which begun a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout one of the Clock in the morning, which favour'd our march ſo well, that we arriv'd at Eight of the Clock in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in ſight of the Enemy, who were ſuprized at our coming, and taking advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their diſorder, I Charg'd them with the Troops of your Houſe, which I led my ſelf to the Battle.</p>
            <p>Now I think on't, <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> ſays his Majeſty, I underſtood that there was one of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Guards who came headlong with his Sword in his hand with a deſign to kill you.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> it is true, and I eſcap'd a ſtroke from him ſo narrowly, that he had undoubtedly taken my Head off, if I had been tall. But as you may, when I am on Horſeback, take me for Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Scarron,</hi> I eaſily put by that blow in crying out with a full Throat, Fire upon that bold Fellow.</p>
            <p>But, ſays his Majeſty, you dearly then bought the glory that you had to keep the Field about half an hour, by the death of my beſt Officers, and of a great number of brave perſons of my Houſe.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:175367:28"/>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> your Majeſty has long ſince uſed your ſelf, to loſe a great m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny Men when you would have the advantage over your Enemies.</p>
            <p>As it is my Maxime to attack them or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily three againſt one, and that the Enemies who ſee themſelves almoſt always inferiour and more feeble in number by half, fight alſo like Madmen, that's the reaſon your Majeſty loſes more men than they; but ſtill you have the Glory on your ſide.</p>
            <p>But, ſays his Majeſty, if theſe loſſes are frequent, and that the War ſhould laſt four or five Campaigns, as in all appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance it will, I run a riſque to ſee my ſelf without Officers and Souldiers.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> your Majeſty muſt bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Peace at any rate, ſhould it coſt even half your Sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ects.</p>
            <p>But, anſwers his Majeſty, I had then rather hazard a general Battle, and come orderly into an open Campaign in the Face of my En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mies.</p>
            <p>I am perſwaded that they would not refuſe it, and that would be infinitely more glorious and worthier of the name of Great, that I bear; imitating in that <hi>Charles Martel</hi> who acquir'd that name by reaſon of his martial humour, and of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:175367:29"/> great actions he did at the Battle of <hi>Tours,</hi> where the <hi>French</hi> kill'd a hundred and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty five thouſand <hi>Moors,</hi> that lay dead on the Spot. It ſeems to me that an Action like that would be incomparably better than all the Tricks and Wiles that I have made uſe of till now, which are no more after all than ſmall Rencounters, which decide nothing, and only lengthen the War.</p>
            <p>No, Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> that is not the way by which I pretend to conduct your Majeſty, your Enemies would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire no better.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> would Triumph with joy, and your Majeſty cannot do them a greater favour, than to come as you ſay into an open field.</p>
            <p>There wants but only one ſuch like Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to annihilate, in an inſtant, all thoſe Prodigies of glory, and to loſe ſo many brave Conqueſts heap'd up, one upon the other, which haſt coſt ſo many Men and ſo much Blood; and I am perſuaded that your Majeſty has not yet forgot what it coſt <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, and St. <hi>Louis,</hi> for having expos'd themſelves a little too much.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:175367:29"/>
            <p>How then, ſays his Majeſty, do you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it? for we muſt take the ſhorteſt way; my People begin to be able to do no more, and Mony becomes ſcarce in my Kingdom; and as we ſay, foreſight is the Mother of Wiſdom; I know what it coſt me in 1672 for having ſtaid a little too long.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> doth your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty abſolutely wiſh to have a peace? I have already pray'd you ſeveral times to diſcover to me your moſt ſecret inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>You know, ſays his Majeſty, that I wiſh it paſſionately. But I reſerve to my ſelf the glory to grant it to my Enemies, and I fight only at preſent to conſtrain them to come and demand it of me.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> ſince it is ſo that your Majeſty is abſolutely reſolved to have a peace; that you wiſh it, and ſeek after it, this is the way to come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to it. Your Majeſty muſt then at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent make <hi>Flanders</hi> the Seat of War; you muſt gather together your greateſt force, and you muſt reckon to have three Armies this Campaign, to act in concert and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to aſſiſt one another.</p>
            <p>Each of theſe Armies muſt be at the leaſt fifty thouſand Men.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:175367:30"/>
            <p>For this purpoſe your Majeſty muſt give Orders to Monſieur <hi>Voiſin,</hi> Intendant of the Low Countries, to make with the Commiſſaries of Proviſions, an exact computation of Proviſions neceſſary for the maintenance of ſo many Troops, and to furniſh the Magazines, of which the Principle ones ſhall be at <hi>Mons, Maubeuge, Philipville,</hi> and <hi>Dinant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great Maſter of the Ordinance muſt alſo give order that the Ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of War, as well as the great Artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be tranſported early to the neareſt frontier places; The Count <hi>de Guiſcard</hi> Governour of <hi>Dinant</hi> muſt take care to aſſemble and get ready a good number of Boats. Monſieur <hi>de Vertillac</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of <hi>Mons</hi> muſt likewiſe take care to get together all the Waggons and Carts which can be found in the Country of <hi>Hainault:</hi> He muſt make at the ſame time as well as the other Governours, a liſt of the Pioneers that we can have, the number of which cannot be leſs than Twenty thouſand; and to the end that all the Troops may be there at the time of the general Rendevouſe which ſhall be at <hi>Mons,</hi> your Majeſty muſt preſently diſpatch Orders to make them march. I add alſo, that care muſt be taken to have
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:175367:30"/> good intelligence to ſtir them up and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them, coſt what it will, becauſe it is the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> without which we ſhall build upon a Quickſand.</p>
            <p>All theſe Reſolutions being taken, there will want nothing but a Head to move ſo great a Body: And as the preſence of Kings and Princes is the Soul and ſtrength of their Army, and that a Prince which commands in perſon his Armies, aſpires to an immortal glory, ſo there is not a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier who fighting in the ſight of his Prince, doth not employ all his valour and being animated with a deſire of glory, and hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to be liberally recompens'd, doth not preſent himſelf with joy, to the greateſt and moſt dangerous perils.</p>
            <p>I adviſe then your Majeſty to make this Campaign as you did that of <hi>Mons;</hi> your Majeſty took notice that this important place was ſurrendred in leſs than fifteen Days, after the opening of the Trenches, in the ſight of an Enemies Army, and in a time where the rigours of the Seaſon oppos'd you.</p>
            <p>After ſuch a blow your Majeſty may undertake what you pleaſe. That's very well, ſays his Majeſty, but where do you judge it will be neceſſary to open the Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ign? ſhall it be by the Siege of <hi>Ath,</hi> or
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:175367:31"/> 
               <hi>Charleroy?</hi> as theſe places are neareſt, it ſeems that we muſt begin there.</p>
            <p>No Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> you muſt attack your Enemies in a more ſenſible part, <hi>Ath</hi> and <hi>Charleroy</hi> are places which will fall of themſelves into your Majeſties Hands.</p>
            <p>What muſt be done then, ſays his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, ſhall we go to <hi>Bombard Bruſſels?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh;</hi> that is not worth while, it muſt be a more ſhining enterprize, it is not reaſonable your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſhould put your ſelf at the head of your Armie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for ſo ſmall a matter.</p>
            <p>What then ſays, his Majeſty, ſhall we At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack <hi>Oſtend</hi> by Sea and by Land? this loſs will be very ſenſible to my Enemies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that is the place where all the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Troops come to Land, and from thence we may penetrate into the Heart of the County of <hi>Flanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt is not important enough to imploy a King with an Army of one hundred and fifty thouſand Men.</p>
            <p>What ſhall be done then, ſays his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty? ſhall we enter into the Country of <hi>Liege</hi> to force the Prince of that Dioceſs to lay down his Arms, and to ſubmit himſelf to my clemency?</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:175367:31"/>
            <p>No, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> that expedition is more proper for <hi>Boufflers</hi> than your Majeſty, it is not glorious enough for a Prince who marches only to attack invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible places.</p>
            <p>Ha! What then ſays his Majeſty?</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh;</hi> your Majeſty muſt come at the Head of one hundred and fifty thouſand Men divided into three Bodies, the firſt of which ſhall be commanded by your Majeſty, having un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you the <hi>Mareſchall d' Humieres.</hi> The the ſecond ſhall be under the Command of the Marqueſs <hi>de B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ufflers,</hi> and the third ſhall be remitted to my Conduct.</p>
            <p>The Army being thus divided the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>de Boufflers</hi> ſhall take the Van with a Body of fifteen thouſand Horſe, and poſſeſs the paſſages and avenues. The main Body of the Army being arriv'd your Majeſty ſhall form the Siege of <hi>Namur,</hi> and by the taking of that impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant place, you will render your ſelf Maſter of a whole County, which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contradiction the fineſt of the Low Countries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> ſays his Majeſty, this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe is great, and this place ſeems to me Impregnable by it Situation; beſides the building of a certain Fort which is called
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:175367:32"/> 
               <hi>Fort William,</hi> built within this little while renders it almoſt inacceſſible.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> Art and Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence muſt favour force, and as we ſay, ſow the Tail of the Fox to the Skin of the Lyon.</p>
            <p>I know an expedient by which half of theſe difficulties will be overcome, and thus it is, as I underſtand it. There is in the Cittadel a certain Baron <hi>de Berſe,</hi> which is a Major, a Man fit to do any thing, a high ſpender, and much given to his pleaſures. I underſtand that this <hi>Berſe</hi> calls himſelf Kinſman of Madam <hi>de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenon,</hi> and that's what we want. But ſays, his Majeſty, who has told you that this <hi>Berſe</hi> will be a fit Man to hold correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence?</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient that he is given to Debauchery. Your Majeſty muſt charge Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> with all this buſineſs; and whilſt we ſhall be preparing Bombs and Carcaſſes, ſhe on her ſide muſt attack the ſtrongeſt part of the place by fair and good guilded Letters, which will do more in one day than an Army of one hundred and fifty thouſand Men in ſix weeks.</p>
            <p>Ho! ſays his Majeſty, if matters be ſo, my good and dear <hi>Maintenon</hi> will do
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:175367:32"/> that well enough to do me a kindneſs.</p>
            <p>But what is it ſhe muſt promiſe him in order to engage him?</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> ſhe muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe him one hundred thouſand Livers for reward, and after the reduction of the place, a Lieutenant Generals Poſt. I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded that he will accept the propoſition, and that in leſs than eight days your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will have convincing proofs thereof.</p>
            <p>Ha! Well ſays his Majeſty; ſuppoſe then for example, that he accepts the offers that <hi>Maintenon</hi> ſhall make him, in your opinion what method muſt he take to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the enterprize?</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> it is this, he muſt in the firſt place make an exact Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter of all the Proviſions and Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions of War, which ſhall be found in the Cittadel; he muſt alſo make a very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular draught of the ſtrength and weakneſs both of the Cittadel, the <hi>Devils Houſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Fort William;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e muſt oppoſe in quality of Major of thc Cittadel, to all that ſhall be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken on the behalf of the Prince of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bancon,</hi> who he muſt alſo endeavour to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, if that can be done.</p>
            <p>He muſt inform your Majeſty or ſome of your Generals, of all the deſigns, marches and countermarches of your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:175367:33"/> he muſt at the ſame time ſeem to do nothing, but to keep himſelf in the Cittadel, and at his ordinary Poſt, juſt till you give him notice that the Mine is to be ſprung.</p>
            <p>Which being done, Madam <hi>de Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> muſt write to him ſome time before to pretend to come out in a Party and ſuffer himſelf to be taken Priſoner, as if it had happen'd by imprudence.</p>
            <p>The Invention is not bad, ſays his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> being thus made Maſter of a Man, who will inform you at bottom of the leaſt Circumſtances, you ought to aſſure your ſelf that from this time forth the place is ſurrendred.</p>
            <p>If that be ſo, ſays his Majeſty, we ſhall have as good a Bargain as that of <hi>Mons.</hi> But the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is about to repaſs the Sea in order to be preſent here early, and by what I can learn here, may put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the Field as ſoon as I; and having a great Army, and being accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd with the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> they may well diſpute this Conqueſt with me; theſe two Princes are of a little hot tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, ſo that this attacking them by ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible an enterpriſe will ſo inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame them
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:175367:33"/> that they will not fail to get together all their Forces to oppoſe me.</p>
            <p>I do not doubt, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> that whilſt this Opera ſhall be playing in <hi>Flanders,</hi> we muſt prepare a Tragedy in <hi>England</hi> for the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Majeſty told me confidently the laſt time that King <hi>James</hi> had receiv'd Letters almoſt from all the Nobility and great ones of the Kingdom; beſides, that there was a great number of <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aticks,</hi> that had all unanimouſly eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Intereſt and Cauſe of this Prince to re-eſtabliſh him upon the Throne, if your Majeſty would only favour and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their enterprize by Eighteen or Twenty Thouſand Men, which would make a Deſcent into the Iſle of <hi>Wight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, ſays his Majeſty, and I have my ſelf read the Letters. A Perſon of Quality ſays in expreſs terms, that his Britiſh Majeſty has nothing to do but to come, that he cannot believe with how much impatience and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs the Grandees of the Kingdom a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the People wait for him; that all the World generally is concern'd for his re-eſtabliſhment upon the Throne. That in ſhort, they begin to make proivſions of Arms and Horſes, which they gather to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the moſt ſecretly the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:175367:34"/> forgetting good Summs of Mony, which they keep ready to pay the Troops to be raiſed in the Kingdom, which ſhall conſiſt only of perſons diſcontented with the preſent Government.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> if the thing be ſo, that will be a great ſtroke; the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> muſt of all neceſſity repaſs the Sea in all haſt to go to the ſuccor of his three Kingdoms, and in the mean time your Majeſty may do your buſineſs without op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and without reſiſtance. Your Majeſty muſt give Orders without loſing of time to the Count <hi>de Tourville</hi> to have the Fleet ready to Sail, and that a great number of Tranſport Ships be got toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in great diligence for the Embarquing of the Troops.</p>
            <p>But ſays, his Majeſty, I ſhall not be very well pleaſed that <hi>Tourville</hi> ſhould run the riſque of a Battle, and I ſee the impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of executing ſuch an enterprize without engaging of the two Fleets, the event whereof gives me trouble to think on't.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> here are great inclinations to a revolution; we muſt hazard, and give ſomething to Fortune. She is too much a Friend of your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties to abandon you in ſo fair a Field.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:175367:34"/>
            <p>Give but your Orders only to <hi>Tourville</hi> to go himſelf to attack the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> if he beats them, as there is all appearance he will, they being not more invincible at preſent than they were in 1690, all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet will range themſelves on your ſide, and being Maſters of the Sea, we can make the Deſcent with all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
            <p>But, ſays his Majeſty, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are like Cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the more you careſs them the leſs they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome near you: If it ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that they ſhould change Opinion in the very mom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt of the Battle, and that they ſhould joyntly fight with the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> where woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tourville</hi> be, and what would become of my poor Fleet?</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> your Majeſty muſt baniſh out of your imagination any ſuch thought; it is a deceiving fancy, and a Bird of an ill Omen which comes to trouble you. We have ſeen but one ſuch Cataſtrophe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> happen'd to your Majeſty and you have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather reaſon to preſage a Victory than a Defeat.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, ſay his Majeſty, ſince you are of that opinion and that you adviſe me to hazard a Bate, I will give my Orders to <hi>Tourville</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t effect.</p>
            <p>But as to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> buſineſs of <hi>Namur,</hi> it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:175367:35"/> ſeems to me that one Hundred and Fifty Thouſand Men is not enough to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take a Siege of that importance, and to poſſeſs ſo vaſt a ground as that.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> we are not now in a time when they marched with Four or Five Hundred Thouſand fighting Men. We read in the Hiſtory of the Kings of the firſt Race, that <hi>Attila</hi> King of the <hi>Huns</hi> came into the Field with an Army of five Hundred Thouſand men, cauſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be called the Scourge of God; but notwithſtanding this great n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mber, he was defeated by King <hi>Merovee,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd loſt in one Battle two Hundred Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſand of his Men.</p>
            <p>Sir, it is not the great n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbers that cauſe Battles to be Won; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Army of Fifty Thouſand Men well commanded, and which makes her movem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, will beat one of an Hund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d Thouſand, if there happens a diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rder among them.</p>
            <p>I have often heard ſay of the incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Monſieur <hi>de Turenne,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Army which exceeded the number of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fty Thouſand Men, incommoded herſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral that Govern'd it.</p>
            <p>Beſides Sir, I have mad juſt computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:175367:35"/> of the Troops of your Enemies; I ſuppoſe alſo that they ſhould be put alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they would not then make one Hundred Thouſand Men, ſo that your Majeſty having Fifty Thouſand more, you will be in a condition to Beſiege the place and obſerve their Motions.</p>
            <p>But, ſays his Majeſty, you have ſuppoſed that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> will find himſelf obliged to return in all haſt to <hi>England,</hi> and that conſequently the Enemy having no longer this Prince commanding at their Head, who is their greateſt Spur, would ſtand ſtill unmoveable, contenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Spectators, which is to ſee the Medal juſt on its fair ſide: But I pray let us view the Reverſe, and let us ſuppoſe that he ſhould ſtay at the Head of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, as this Prince has long ſince ſought an occaſion to ſignalize himſelf in, and to give me Battle; ſeeing me engaged in a Seige of this Conſequence, if the fancy ſhould take him to come and attack me, and that I being beat ſhould be obliged to quit it, what ſhame and what confuſion will that be to me, who boaſt my ſelf to have the invincibility of <hi>Achilles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> your Majeſty has nothing leſs to doubt, than that I will make you ſo juſt a draught of the ground,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:175367:36"/> of the Avenues and Defiles which cover the place, that when your Majeſty ſhall be once made Maſter, of them with an Army of one Hundred and Fifty Thouſand Fighting men, as it hath been ſaid, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack you with an Army of Two Hundred Thouſand Men, without hazard of being beaten. Your Majeſty ought to Encamp between the <hi>Sambre</hi> and the <hi>Meufe,</hi> and beſides that you will be cover'd by thoſe two Rivers, you will have at your Right the Army of the Marqueſs <hi>de Bouffters,</hi> which will cover you on that ſide. As to the other Body of the Army, of which I ſhall have the Command, that ſhall poſſeſs all the ground between <hi>Namur</hi> and the ſmall River of <hi>Mehaigne;</hi> which is juſt the only place at which the Enemy can make their Attack, if ſo be they have a mind to it; beſides, many advantages that I could draw from the Situation of the Country, which is cut off by Defiles and Woods, there wants but a ſmall Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to Stop your Enemies, the <hi>Mehaigne</hi> or the <hi>Orme</hi> would ſerve me always for an Obſtacle, ſo that your Majeſty has no cauſe to apprehend any danger I will cover it ſo well with my Army, that you will have no more reaſon to fear, than if you were at <hi>Verſailles,</hi> near your good <hi>Maintenon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:175367:36"/>
            <p>But at leaſt, ſays his Majeſty, you muſt promiſe me to avoid all engaging, and to Encamp your ſelf ſo well, that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> mav rather dream of any other thing than to force you to fight. I am appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of nothing more than of a Battle, and if I ſhould be preſent and happen to loſe it, I ſhould make an irreparable breach to my Glory.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> reſt ſatisfied thereupon.</p>
            <p>Let your Majeſty only give your Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to the end that all may be ready; and that the Troops come early; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe of <hi>Catalonia, Savoy,</hi> and <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> which are the Provinces that are far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt off. As to the event, I take it upon my ſelf, and I will always be anſwerable for it, being perſwaded that this Conqueſt will coſt your Majeſty no more than that of <hi>Mons,</hi> and that you will receive not only great advantages, but that it will put you into an infallible way of obtaining a Peace, which I wiſh with all my Heart.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as Monſieur <hi>de Luxemburgh</hi> was gone out, the King caus'd Monſieur <hi>de Catinat</hi> to be call'd in, and bid him make him in few words, a Report of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in which he left the Affairs of <hi>Savoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:175367:37"/>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>de Catinat</hi> ſays, Sir, I have ſufficiently inform'd your Majeſty by my Letters of the particulars of the War of <hi>Italy,</hi> &amp; of the care that I have taken to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit my ſelf worthily of the Government of your Army with which your Majeſty was willing to Honour me</p>
            <p>And if I had not all the ſucceſs that I could have well wiſhed the laſt Campaign which was that of 1691. I have never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs done as much as lay in any Man's power with ſo ſmall a number as I had. But the arrival of the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> in <hi>Piedmont</hi> ſpoil'd all by the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Germans</hi> which he brought with him, which being joyn'd with the Troops of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Savoy,</hi> Form'd an Army ſtronger than mine by more than half. This inequality of Force ſtop'd immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the happy Progreſs I had made in the beginning of the Campaign; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs without going out of my natural Seat.</p>
            <p>I made all the movements I thought my ſelf oblig'd to make, to cover the Country, to guard the Paſſages, and to ſhun an Engagement, to which they would have drawn me, your Majeſty having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbid me; and that was a great fortune to me to have to do with <hi>Germans,</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:175367:37"/> who gave me the time well to retrench, and to poſſeſs my ſelf of all the Poſts, after having left in <hi>Carmaniole</hi> Four or Five Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men, and cauſed all the Hills and Paſſages of <hi>Suza</hi> to be taken up. As to the Shock your Majeſties Armies ſuffer'd at the Siege of <hi>Coni</hi> (which Monſieur <hi>de Bulonde</hi> had the imprudence to abandon after he had his Trenches open'd againſt it for many days, it was ſufficiently counterba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanc'd by the ſmall progreſs the <hi>Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts</hi> made; becauſe, beſides their coming late into the Field, the miſintelligence which reign'd amongſt their Generals ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely broke the courſe of their Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes which were terminated at the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Carmaniole.</hi> The Extract of their Counſels of War, I had by means of a Penſion which I paid to one of their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, (as I acquainted your Majeſty by a Letter) was of great Service to me, and I made uſe of one Brother <hi>Recolet,</hi> a <hi>German,</hi> by whom I had my be Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondences to receive my Letters by a ſure hand, which were brought to me by one named <hi>Jenet,</hi> a <hi>Savoyard</hi> by Nation, who went and took them in a Trunk of an old Tree, where the brother <hi>Recolet</hi> had took a care to put them. I then underſtood that in their Council of War, in which
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:175367:38"/> the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> preſided joyntly with the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> the Count <hi>de Schom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh</hi> was to command the <hi>Hugneu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> and the old return'd Refugees made this following propoſal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That an irruption ſhould be made into</hi> Dauphine <hi>and</hi> Provence, <hi>go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng thereinto by the Vallie of</hi> Keiras, <hi>after having made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Maſters of the Castle. That from thence they might eaſily ſeize upon the ſmall City of</hi> Guilleſtre; <hi>and that Three Leagues from thence they might continue their march to force the City of</hi> Ambrun, <hi>where there is a very fine Archbiſhoprick. That being once made maſters of the most advantagious places of high</hi> Dauphine, <hi>they ſhould not fail to carry the dread and terrour throughout the whole Province, which being one of the moſt oppreſs'd of</hi> France, <hi>by the Taxes and great Impoſts that it pays to his Majeſty, and ruin'd on the other ſide by the frequent paſſage of the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, it would not fail to riſe and take up Arms againſt her natural Prince. That the great number of new Catholicks which were in that place, would undoubtedly find out a way for a revolt. That as for him he was of this opinion, that there was no time to be loſt, the Seaſon being already advanced but too far; that the places which remain'd behind poſſest by the</hi> French, <hi>would give them no diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:175367:38"/> that they ſhould only leave a good Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Army upon the Frontiers to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cure</hi> Piedmont, <hi>to make Head againſt the Army o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Catinat, <hi>and to keep the Garriſon of</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal <hi>and</hi> Pignerol <hi>in awe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I acknowledge freely Sir, that this Project gave me a great deal of trouble, and that I fear'd very much that the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance would have lean'd to that ſide; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe truly according to the rules of War, and the true intereſts of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and of his Allies, they might thereby cut out a great deal of buſineſs for your Majeſty, and put me out of a condition to oppoſe them, becauſe I ſhould have immediately been obliged to divide the Body of my Army, which was already but too ſmall, and I ſhould have found my ſelf in a condition to have held out the Campaign no longer.</p>
            <p>To come back to the Count <hi>de Schom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh</hi> who had reſolved upon theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions that I have now reported; The Count <hi>Caraffa,</hi> who commanded the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Troop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſpoke immediately after him, and ſaid, <hi>That in truth this Reſolution was judicious, but that it ſeem'd too bold an attempt to undertake entring into an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Country; to force an Army that poſſeſt the Avenues and the paſſages, and which was
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:175367:39"/> advantageouſly intrench'd; beſides that the Winter which came on apace, did not permit that they ſhould at ſo great a diſtance, engage themſelvss in an unknow Country, and run a hazard of being cut off; that they might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an Army to great danger by following the advice of</hi> Schombergh, <hi>and that that was not all, to enter into an Enemies Country, but alſo to bring the Army back again ſafe and ſound. That he did not ſee how they could ſucceed in ſuch p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ojects, whilſt the Enemies ſhould poſſeſs all the neareſt places that made them Maſters of all</hi> Savoy, <hi>and put all</hi> Pied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont <hi>under contribution, if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y had not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways an Army there to cover it. That as for him he was of a quite contrary opinion to that of</hi> Monſieur de Schombergh; <hi>that he did not remember he had read, that the</hi> Caeſars <hi>and the</hi> Alexanders, <hi>who had been great Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, ever practis'd any thing like this in the whole courſe of their Wars: In ſhort, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that it was very proper, with ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to better advice, to begin the Campaign by the Siege of</hi> Carmaniole, <hi>that after that place had yielded, he judg'd it fit that the reſt of the time ſhould be employ'd to treat early for Winter Quarters with the Princes of</hi> Italy; <hi>that the Imperial Troops would be very much fatigued after ſuch a Siege, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:175367:39"/> would be then only fit for nothing elſe but to take up their Winter Quarters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Count <hi>de Schombergh</hi> being mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the Prince of <hi>Orange's</hi> intereſt, who had ſent him into <hi>Savoy</hi> to put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at the Head of the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> could not without being concern'd hear what Count <hi>Caraffa</hi> propos'd; and altho he was of a ſweet and pacifick temper, a quality which he inherited from his deceaſed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as well as that that gave great hopes of his being one of the beſt Captains of the Age, could not nevertheleſs perſuade himſelf to be quiet; he had too long ſeen himſelf idle againſt his will. Beſides, he could not get it into his head whatever, he tryd to force himſelf to believe, that a whole Campaign ought to be paſs'd in the Siege of ſo ſmall a place as <hi>Carmaniolle,</hi> whilſt they ſhould neglect one of the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt occaſions that ever was offer'd for the Allies to enter into <hi>France.</hi> He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd then to all that had been propos'd by Count <hi>Caraffa, that he was too old a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitioner in War not to have a full knowledg of the Situation of the Country, of the Roads, of the Woods, of the Marſhes, of the Defiles, of the Mountains, of the Rivers, of the Bridges, of the watry places—, of the Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and in one word of all the places by which
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:175367:40"/> they can pretend to enter into</hi> Dauphine: <hi>He added to this his knowledg, that of having ſtudied from his youth, the Genius, the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the intereſt; the jealouſies, the ſtrength, and the weakneſs, and generally all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant Paſſions of the</hi> French <hi>Nation, in which he had been brought up. That a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of ſome conſideration, and who strove to understand his Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de, ought thoroughly to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with theſe things. And that he ſhould be very ſorry to have it diſputed w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th him by another; that if he ſhould be obliged to ſupport his diſcourſe by examples drawn from the greateſt Captai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, he could make it appear as clear as the Sun at Noon, that the</hi> Caeſars <hi>and the</hi> Alexanders, <hi>as well as</hi> Charles <hi>the Fifth, the</hi> Turennes <hi>and the</hi> Condes, <hi>and infinite other modern Generals have not had any other Principle in the Art of War, That he propos'd nothing raſhly; but he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to give to the Council ſo juſt a draught of the deſign they propos'd, that he was perſuaded it was not ſo much to be rejected as the Count</hi> Caraffa <hi>would have inſinuated.</hi> Thereupon putting his Hand in his Pock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et he pull'd out many Writings. The firſt was a circular Letter in form of a Manifeſto, which was to be diſpers'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their coming into the Country to ſtir up the People to embrace the party of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:175367:40"/> Allies, which was conceiv'd in theſe terms.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That all the Inhabitants of High and Low</hi> Dauphine <hi>were exhorted to come and joyn the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ms of his</hi> Britannick <hi>Majesty, and of his Royal Highneſs the Duke of</hi> Savoy, <hi>who came with a pote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Army to their relief, to help them to ſhake off the Yoke, under which they had groan'd ſo many years. That the old Catholicks as well as the new Converts, without diſtincti n of Religion ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d be equally received by the clemency of theſe Princes who tender'd them their aſſistance; That God had already on many occaſions declar'd himſelf the Protector of the Armies of the Allies, and that they ought n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to doubt but that he would bleſs their conquests and put them quickly into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to deliver all</hi> France <hi>from her great op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they protested that nothing in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Religion ſhould be changed, but that every one ſhould have full liberty of conſcience, like that the People ſo peaceably enjoyed in the reigns of</hi> Henry <hi>the Fourth and</hi> Louis <hi>in the Thirteenth. They declared alſo that all the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>btors ſhould be diſcharged who ſhould ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves, and come and implore the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of their Deliverers; and laſtly, that they would maintain the Clergy in their dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, the Gentlemen in their Lands, the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:175367:41"/> Merchants in the freedom of their Trade, the Countrymen in peace and quiet, and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates in their Authority for the preſerving of the Law and the Adminiſtration of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they ſhould live under a Government far different from that in which they had liv'd, and that they ſhould at once be delivered from the great miſeries to which they had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd, by the inſupportable and Tyrannical charge of Taxes and Impoſts which they were obliged to pay to a Sovereign, who had made his free People, miſerable Slaves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the reading of this Manifeſto, he ſhewed ſeveral Letters, which had been written to him by the moſt conſiderable of the Nobility of high and low <hi>Dauphine,</hi> the chief whereof were alſo read in the Council according to order, as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Copy of a Letter written from <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phine</hi> to Monſieur the Count of <hi>Schom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh,</hi> at preſent in <hi>Piedmont.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> write to you with Tears of joy which have ſucceeded thoſe of ſorrow, of which your happy arrival in <hi>Savoy</hi> hath altogether cured us, in hopes that your dear preſence will more and more favour the good intentions
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:175367:41"/> of his Royal Highneſs, for the good of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace, and the deliverance of ſo many Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Slaves, whoſe ſighs have oftentimes come as far as you, even when you were yet in <hi>Brandenburgh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But it was too early Days then, ſince that the providence of God has reſerv'd you till this Day, to be one of the Principal Inſtruments made uſe of to reſtore to our Poor <hi>Sion,</hi> her antient ſplend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r and tranquillity. We heartily pray to God that he would be pleaſed to take you into his Holy Protection, and would bleſs all your juſt deſigns. You cannot believe the inclinations in which the generality and almoſt every one of the whole province find themſelves; they ſeem to me altogether favourable if you were a little diligent, and that you would once imitate <hi>France</hi> in that, to whom all moments are precious, when ſhe is about to execute her deſigns.</p>
                  <p>I engage you my word upon the Faith of a Man of Honour, that there would be a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral riſing, if you would enter into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. The fear I am in leſt my Letter ſhould miſcarry, doth not give me leave to ſend you the particulars of all things; rely upon the little I have ſaid; let me know the time and place, and believe me without reſerve <hi>Sir,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Monſieur <hi>Julian</hi> will give you my Name and Direction how to ſend to me.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:175367:42"/>
                  <head>Another Written to the ſame.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WE are under the greateſt trouble in the World, to understand that the deſign you had verbally propos'd to his Electoral High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Bavaria</hi> and to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> to enter into <hi>Dauphine</hi> by the Valley of <hi>Keiras,</hi> was not receiv'd as you expected, and as we wiſh'd. We earneſtly pray you as many as we are, the number whereof is ſo great that you would be ſurprized if I ſhould tell you; but as that doth not concern the condition of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair in hand, I deſire you to excuſe me for ſeveral reaſons. We ſupplicate you, I ſay, unanimouſly to come back to your Post, and to be willing once more to employ your intereſt to make their Highneſſes and Count <hi>Caraffa</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that it is ſo important a thing to enter into <hi>Dauphin</hi> this Campaign, taking advantage of the weakneſs of the places, of the good diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in which the People are at preſent found, and of an aſſured Conqueſt of the whole Country, if you come ſtreight to <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble,</hi> that if you neglect it, I do Propheſie there will remain no more to the Allies than an immort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l diſſatisfaction for having gone no farther, when you might have penetrated even into the Heart of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:175367:42"/>
                  <p>We have written ſeveral Letters upon the ſame Subject to Meſſieurs <hi>de Monbrun</hi> and <hi>de Montauban,</hi> praying them to Communicate them to you; I am</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     <signed>Yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Count <hi>Caraffa</hi> ſeeing that Monſieur <hi>de Schomberg</hi> came immediately to matter of fact, and that he maintain'd his Opinion by ſtrong proofs, and remarking be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that his Electoral Highneſs of <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> the Prince <hi>Eugene,</hi> the Duke <hi>de Leganez,</hi> the Count <hi>de Palfi,</hi> and the Marqueſs <hi>de Pianeſe,</hi> who were all preſent, ſeem'd in ſome meaſure to be willing to applaud him, withdrew im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately out of the Council, and went home, proteſting that he would remain firm in his firſt reſolution; that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil might reſolve what they thought fit; but for him he knew what he had to do, and that the Imperial Troops of which he had the chief Command, ſhould make no other motion than what he ſhould or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them; that he knew the Emperour's mind, and ſo it was needleſs to loſe time in employing it to deliberate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.</p>
            <p>This way of procedure, which was ſo little expected, extreamly ſurpriz'd
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:175367:43"/> the other Generals. But the Count <hi>de Schomberg</hi> appear'd ſo ſenſibly touch'd at it, that he without any more ado preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly complain'd, and alſo afterwards ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted them, that he was ſo little ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in <hi>Italy,</hi> that he e'en reſolv'd to go back into <hi>Holland,</hi> or into <hi>Brandenbourg,</hi> where he had formerly Commanded the Troops of his Electoral Highneſs of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denbourg.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> was no leſs concern'd, that after having Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led through all <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> to come by hard Journeys into <hi>Piedmont,</hi> where he was expected with ſuch impatience, which he did, notwithſtanding the acceſs of a Fever, which he found very hard to get rid of, without reckoning a Thouſand other unhappy mifortunes which he felt, during the length of his Journey: And all this in hopes to have gather'd Lawrels at his Arrival; if he met with nothing leſs, that he muſt reſt contented, as alſo his other Companions, with an Idea only which they formed to themſelves of a Glorious Campaign.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> was he who loſt moſt by theſe Diſputes, and whom the matter touch'd neareſt; but as he had not the experience of other Generals, he found himſelf not in a condition with a heat
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:175367:43"/> proper for the cauſe, to maintain an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſo plauſible and ſo diſintereſted as that of Count <hi>Scomberg</hi>'s appear'd.</p>
            <p>Beſides, he was willing to conſent to it, becauſe they look'd upon this undertaking as the only remedy which preſented it ſelf to incommode their Enemy, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their poor States from the Inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable burthen of the Auxiliary Troops, which would Triumph with Joy, ſaid he, if they ſhould ſee themſelves once Poſted in the Enemies Country, to take their Winter Quarters there, which is juſt the grievance of the <hi>Germans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the bitter Draught that Count <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raffa</hi> could not ſwallow, was quite another thing. He ſaw amongſt the Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> plenty enough of all things. It is a Country flowing with Milk and Hony; whereas in <hi>Dauphine,</hi> he ſaw nothing but Melancholy Deſerts, and People already ruin'd by the War, which was more than ſufficient to make him take another reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Eugene</hi> was of the Opinion of the Duke his Couſin, and their intereſts were too common, not to be united toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He added that he could not think ſelf-willdneſs was capable to produce ſo great diſorders, and that Princes were
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:175367:44"/> happy when they were the only Maſters, and the Armies Victorious, when they were Commanded by one Chief; that theſe three years that the Wars continu'd in <hi>Italy</hi> their diſagreement had alone done more hurt than the Enemy; for 'twas this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Goddeſs of Diſcord that came inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly to trouble the moſt important re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, and to furniſh new Seeds of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion and Diſpute, which oftentimes ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from a ſlight occaſion: That if theſe conteſts ſhould be kept up any longer, and that we ſhould amuſe our ſelves thus to paſs whole Campaigns in deliberating, and principally the precious time which was deſtin'd to enter into Action, This would be juſt to play the Game which <hi>France</hi> would deſire; that we draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves inſenſibly into Winter, which is the Mother of buſineſs for her, ſhe would have a new occaſion to cry out as ſhe uſe to do of Victory, becauſe ſhe is aſſured of her deſign, and takes juſtly the time of our Retreat and lying in our Winter Quarters.</p>
            <p>The Duke <hi>de Leganez</hi> Governour of the <hi>Milaneſe</hi> was altogether of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Opinion, (that is to ſay) <hi>Piano veremo,</hi> and being full of confidence and good will, he catch't at all, and was ready to embrace
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:175367:44"/> the firſt or ſecond reſolution, or elſe both together, if that could have been done and agreed to with good Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But as the good Man is as great a Wit, as was his Predeceſſor, ſo he ſeems to have a little more good nature, and the glorious Houſe from which he is deſcended ſerves him for a Pattern; he contents himſelf nevertheleſs to follow the Crowd and plurality of Voices, for fear to fall into ſome Hereſie, if he ſhould have dar'd to have advanc'd from his own Opinion a third project. In a word, the reſolution taken to enter into <hi>France,</hi> was the moſt proper for him, and for all the other States of <hi>Italy.</hi> And if the Count <hi>de Caraffa</hi> would by misfortune have yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to it, that had been done. But as I have already inſinuated to your Majeſty, I had ſo well fetter'd him with Chains of Gold, that he ſaw himſelf not in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to make one ſingle Step towards it. Count <hi>Palfi,</hi> a good <hi>German</hi> alſo, otherwiſe a brave Man, and the Marquiſs <hi>de Pianeſe,</hi> were abſolutely of the Opinion of Count <hi>Schomberg,</hi> and could not conſent to the <hi>Negative</hi> without regret.</p>
            <p>The buſyneſs having then been tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers'd by the ſelfconceitedneſs of Count
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:175367:45"/> 
               <hi>Caraffa,</hi> who, as I have repreſented it, had no Body with him; but as he had on his ſide all the Imperial Troops which made the principal Force of their Army, he conſtrain'd all the other Generals in ſpight of all they had to ſay, to ſubmit to the Law of his Judgment; ſo that not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to do otherwiſe, they reſolv'd at laſt to act joyntly with him, and to open the Campaign by the Siege of <hi>Carma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noille,</hi> of which they made themſelves Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters after a great deal of reſiſtance, from a part of your Majeſties Troops which fought bravely.</p>
            <p>After this Conqueſt they talk'd no more of any Project for the reſt of the Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign. <hi>Caraffa</hi> keeping faithfully his word which he had ſo ſolemnly ſworn, would hear talk of nothing more but Winter Quarters, for fear of violating his Oath, and paſſing for a perjur'd Perſon; ſo putting immediately his Hand to the Work, he began to treat about Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions with the Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> who finding themſelves in more trouble than if they had an Enemies Army at their Gates, found no better way to take, to preſerve Peace and repoſe in their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, than to conſent to the payment of great Summs which they demanded of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:175367:45"/> them, rather than to ſee their Inhabitants expos'd to the Inſolence and Fury of the Souldiers, who were ready to fall upon them as upon Innocent Doves.</p>
            <p>The Republick of <hi>Genoua,</hi> and the Dukes of <hi>Mantua</hi> and <hi>Modena</hi> will for a good while remember the coming of the <hi>Germans</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi> and the other States will have no reaſon to forget them.</p>
            <p>But to make ſhort, ſince your Majeſty orders me, and that the time to make your deſigns appear this Campaign, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacheth, I will add only to all I have ſaid already concerning the Affairs of <hi>Italy,</hi> that I thought fit, as I have let your Majeſty know, to make advantage of the diſtance of the <hi>German</hi> Troops which were found diſpers'd here and there in ſeveral Countries, and to lay Siege to <hi>Montmelian,</hi> and ſecure by this important Fort the Conqueſts with which it had pleas'd God to bleſs your Arms in <hi>Savoy.</hi> I undertook then this Siege in a time, when the rigors of the Seaſon making us feel the utmoſt extremity, not to ſpeak of a great number of other unhappy ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles, which ſeem'd to oppoſe ſo great an undertaking, I found my ſelf ſeveral times oblig'd to quit it; but as your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:175367:46"/> had expreſly order'd me to hazard all, I at laſt made it ſubmit to your obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in leſs time than I had propos'd to my ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Catinat,</hi> anſwer me, I pray you, ſays the King, to what I ſhall ask you. I have a great deſign in <hi>Flanders</hi> that I pretend to execute ſome weeks hence, and for this purpoſe I ſhall have occaſion for an Army of one hundred and fifty thouſand Men. As the Troops that I have in <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> are not ſufficient to make this number, may I well diſpoſe of fifteen or ſixteen thouſand Men of the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oops which are under your command in <hi>Savoy?</hi> As you are the only one of all my Generals who knows the Map of <hi>Italy</hi> beſt, the deſigns of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the Genius of the <hi>Italian</hi> Nation, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing travel'd in the habit of a <hi>Carmelite</hi> thro' all thoſe Countries, according to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der I had given you, in hopes that you would be one day more proper to do me important Services on that ſide, and it was you who had the care of the buying of the City of <hi>Cazal,</hi> having received the Sum which I had agreed with the Duke of <hi>Mantoua</hi> to pay unto him for it.</p>
            <p>Anſwer me, I pray you, do you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me to be in a condition ſafe enough
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:175367:46"/> to withdraw my Troops, and could you well make head againſt the <hi>Germans,</hi> if I only leave you an Army of nine thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men?</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Catinat,</hi> your Province of <hi>Dauphine,</hi> which was the moſt expos'd of all your Kingdom, and into which your Enemies have often flatter'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to enter with a great Army, need to fear nothing further, ſince the tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Monmelian.</hi> This place as well as <hi>Pignerol, Suſa</hi> and <hi>Nice,</hi> of the ſide of <hi>Provence,</hi> are more than ſufficient to cover it and to put all into a profound ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>But let us turn the Scale, ſays his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty: If the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> making advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of your weakneſs and of the ſmall number you will have there, ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen on a ſudden to take a Reſolution of forcing the Paſſages, and of entring into my Kingdom, and that jointly with <hi>Schombergh,</hi> who commands the <hi>Hugonots</hi> and the old return'd Refugees they ſhould come to enter into <hi>Dauphi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> and put all that Province under Contribution; for without flatteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g my ſelf I fear the old return'd Refugees, and my new Converts coming once to form themſelves into Troops, and to joyn them, would m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:175367:47"/> a formidable Army, for they would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure me a great deal of trouble, and might in time make this Province to riſe, which is already but too much diſaffected, becauſe it is that part of my Kingdom that I have always the leaſt minded, and which has been the moſt oppreſs'd by the great Taxes that it pays me, and lately by the paſſage of the Souldiers and the Winter Quarters which has almoſt made them deſolate. That if once this Barrier come to be forc'd, my Enemies might from <hi>Dauphine</hi> enter into the Country of <hi>Lyons,</hi> Foreſts and Boucollois, all being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen on that ſide, and do me more hurt in one Campaign than I have done to them ſince the War was declar'd.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwers <hi>Catinat,</hi> reſt ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this, and let not your Majeſty for this ſtop the courſe of your great under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings: I will take care of <hi>Dauphine;</hi> give me only the charge of it, as you have done for the time paſs'd, and confide en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely in me.</p>
            <p>But, ſays the King, you may be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Catirat.</hi> Do not you know that Men alter, as well as their Opinions, and that ſuch a Reſolution is quickly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken?</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:175367:47"/>
            <p>Sir, anſwers <hi>Catinat,</hi> that your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty may not trouble you ſelf, I engage you my word upon the Faith of an honeſt Man, that your Enemies ſhall undertake nothing on that ſide, and that the diſunion amongſt them will always be the ruin of their undertakings.</p>
            <p>I wiſh it might be ſo, ſays his Majeſty; for if I were aſſured of the contrary, I would chuſe rather to remain all the Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign upon the defenſive, waiting for the Winter to make a Siege, than to ſuffer that my Enemies ſhould give me on that ſide any blemiſh to my glory; and that a Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> whom I formerly treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as one of my Pages, ſhould boaſt to have encamp'd at the Gates of <hi>Grenoble:</hi> I believe I ſhould dye with grief if that ſhould come to my Ears: For what ſhame would not that be to receive Law from a Prince to whom I gave it all the courſe of my Reign?</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Catinat,</hi> I add for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, that your Majeſty needs not to fear any thing from the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> nor from the old return'd Refugees. Your Majeſty has given me with the Command of your Army a golden Key, which has the ſecret to open the Hearts, and as the head of <hi>Meduſa</hi> to convert Men into Rocks
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:175367:48"/> and make them immoveable; ſo that when the Skin of the Lion ſhall fail me, I ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways have that of the Fox, and that will be more than ſufficient to ſtop all the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings of the <hi>Savoyards</hi> and <hi>Germans,</hi> if ſo be they ſhould ſeem to undertake more than the laſt Campaign. I add to all theſe Reflections, that they being uſed to come into the Field after that the Troops of your Majeſty have done their buſineſs, if occaſion ſhould require it, it would always be time enough to form an Army of Detachments, that we ſhall have to oppoſe them in all their deſigns. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, I will manage ſo well the nine thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand that your Majeſty ſhall leave me, and I will cauſe Monſieur <hi>de la Rai, de Bache Villiers,</hi> and <hi>de Vins</hi> to go to their Poſts who ſhall cover the Province ſo advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geouſly that we ſhall have nothing to fear.</p>
            <p>The King being ſufficiently inform'd of the affairs of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> paſs'd to thoſe of <hi>Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talonia,</hi> and ſaid in preſence of Monſieur <hi>de Catinat,</hi> that he had not judg'd it fit to call Monſieur <hi>de Nouailles</hi> to this Council of War, becauſe that having nothing to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend from the part of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> but ſome feeble Rodomontades, and that the Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa</hi> their General, having more care to ſay his Prayers by his
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:175367:48"/> great <hi>Pater Noster</hi> Beads, which he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries hanging at the Guard of his Sword, than of the Stratagems of War, he had alſo made choice of a General fitter to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate the Affairs of the Houſe of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Poor Madam <hi>de Fontange,</hi> of which he had the charge whilſt ſhe liv'd, than to have commanded an Army any thing conſiderable; that having beſides given the Government of <hi>Languedoc</hi> to his keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and that even till one of the three young Princes ſhould be of age to fill it, he was willing alſo to give him the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Army in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> as well by reaſon of the nearneſs of the place, as alſo of the knowledge which he hath of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tongue and Manners. But he had ſo ſmall a number in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> that it was not worth while to talk of it; that at moſt we might reckon upon three thouſand Men of eight that were there; the five thouſand remaining being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to make the Campaign, and to act againſt the <hi>Miquelets.</hi> His Majeſty added, that it was true, that he had advice by the means of his Spies at the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> that the Catholick King caus'd a Fleet to be Arm'd of 14 or 15 Men of War, which were to be jointly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded with the Gallies, by Admiral
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:175367:49"/> 
               <hi>Papichini,</hi> to cruiſe in the <hi>Medditerranean,</hi> from the moment that the Count <hi>d' Estrees</hi> ſhould be put to Sea, and that they ſeem'd to have a mind to attempt ſomething upon the Coaſt of <hi>Provence</hi> to favour the Duke of <hi>Savoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that he gave ſo little Faith to all thoſe diſcourſes, that he made no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to ſay, that ſince they had undertaken nothing like it the two laſt Campaigns, it was a proof of their weakneſs, and that he had by conſequence nothing to fear on that ſide. From the affairs of <hi>Catalonia,</hi> his Majeſty came to thoſe of <hi>Germany,</hi> and order'd immediately that <hi>Catinat</hi> ſhould go out of the Chamber, and that the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchal de Lorge</hi> ſhould come in, who commanded his Army upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and ſaid to him, <hi>de Lorge,</hi> I pray you tell me a word of the condition in which you left <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Troops.</p>
            <p>Sir, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>wer'd <hi>de Lorge,</hi> your Army upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> has ſuffer'd much by the diſeaſes which have Reign'd all this Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign, and alſo it finds its ſelf much weaken'd by the Death of ſo great a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of brave Officers and Souldiers; not to ſpeak of the deſertion which has been alſo very great, notwithſtanding any thing we could do to hinder it. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:175367:49"/> by the care that the Marqueſs <hi>d' <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xelles,</hi> Monſieur <hi>de Melac</hi> and I have taken, your Majeſties Army is at preſent in an incomparable better condition than it was</p>
            <p>We have given it good Winter Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which has much contributed to it's refreſhment, and cauſe the Diſeaſes to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate: After that we have ſet our ſelves to work with heat and ſucceſs to make the neceſſary recruits to render the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments compleat, and that by the means of Mony, which we are to conſider in that Country as the <hi>Materia prima,</hi> and the ſecond cauſe, which makes that it is ador'd among the <hi>Germans,</hi> and that by this means your Majeſty will never want Souldiers.</p>
            <p>The King ſeeing Monſieur <hi>de Melac,</hi> who followed the Mareſchal <hi>de Lorge,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs'd himſelf to him, and ſaid to him, <hi>Melac,</hi> have you brought a Liſt of the Villages that you have burnt in <hi>Germany,</hi> and particularly in the <hi>Palatinate</hi> and along the <hi>Rhine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Melac</hi> anſwer'd, Sir, I have not yet made it, but if your Majeſty deſires it, I will make one immediately.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty anſwer'd him, you will do me a kindneſs, and you muſt take care at the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:175367:50"/> ſame time to mark thoſe that remain to be burnt.</p>
            <p>Afterwards his Majeſty addreſs'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Marqueſs <hi>d' <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xelles,</hi> who had likewiſe follow'd the Duke <hi>de Lorge,</hi> and ſaid to him, <hi>d' <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xelles,</hi> I am not altogether ſatisfied with the way of your living, and I have heard many diſadvantagious things to your Reputation; for I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd every day that you plunge your ſelf into the dirty Debaucheries of the Duke <hi>de Vendoſme;</hi> altho' on the other ſide I do not diſlike your Services; and I have given you ſufficient marks by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring upon you the charge of Lieutenant General, in memory of the Siege of <hi>Mayence,</hi> that you defended ſeven weeks together againſt an Army of one hundred thouſand Men, which had at their Head the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and all the Electors of the Empire.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs <hi>d' <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xelles</hi> anſwer'd, Sir, I very well ſee that I have great Enemies at Court: But I pray your Majeſty to be perſuaded that all theſe falſe reports that have come to your Ears, do owe their Birth only to the jealouſy and miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of ſome Generals, whom I ſhall name in time and place, in order to clear my ſelf when your Majeſty ſhall pleaſe to order me.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:175367:50"/>
            <p>His Majeſty anſwered, the time is too ſhort to enter into ſuch a diſcuſſion; grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter affairs call me into <hi>Flanders;</hi> ſo I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to inform my ſelf of all theſe matters at my return from the Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign.</p>
            <p>After which his Majeſty turning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf towards Monſieur the Duke <hi>de Lorge,</hi> ſaid to him, <hi>de Lorge,</hi> I have call'd you to aſſiſt in this Council of War to reveal to you a great deſign. I have reſolv'd to march into <hi>Flanders</hi> at the Head of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of one hundred and fifty thouſand Men; the time preſſes, and the undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is important, ſo I ſhall have occaſion for all my Forces. I have already given orders to make all the regulate Troops to come, that I have in <hi>Italy,</hi> except nine thouſand Men; for according to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that <hi>Catinat</hi> has juſt now made me, I judge that my Enemies will undertake nothing on that ſide.</p>
            <p>Beſides, that I have let the Duke <hi>de Nouailles</hi> know that my will was that he ſhould make a Detachment of three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men, of his beſt Troops, and that he ſhould make them march apace, to the end they might be in the nick of time at the Rendevouſe.</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:175367:51"/>
            <p>The buſineſs in Hand then is to know the number of the Troops of my Army in <hi>Germany,</hi> the Detachment that you are in a condition to make, and thoſe you have occaſion for to cover my Conqueſts with on that ſide.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd the Mareſchal <hi>de Lorge,</hi> your Majeſties Army in <hi>Germany</hi> may amount to about fifty thouſand Men, reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning the Garriſons of <hi>Strasbourg,</hi> of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipsbourg,</hi> and the other places; ſo you may depend upon a Detachment of twenty or twenty five thouſand Men; the other twenty five thouſand which remain ſhall be order'd for the preſervation of the Country, of which I can at any time form an Army of ten thouſand Men, which will be more than ſufficient to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Enemy, and the reſt ſhall be diſtributed in the Garriſons of the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier places.</p>
            <p>But, anſwer'd his Majeſty, could not the <hi>Germans</hi> during that time make uſe of your weakneſs and undertake the Siege of <hi>Philipsbourg,</hi> or <hi>Landaw,</hi> or elſe <hi>Mont Royal,</hi> that the deceaſed Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> look'd upon as the Flower of all my Fortreſſes, and inſomuch that he was reſolv'd to have it at any rate? Or at leaſt can they not make ſome conſiderable ravage in the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:175367:51"/> Country, and oblige me to quit a great undertaking half begun? As I do not march unprofitably, but to gather Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, and that Victory may follow me wherever I go, I ſhould have an inconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable trouble, if a Reverſe ſhould happen to me, and that that ſhould fall out for having fail'd of good Intelligence.</p>
            <p>Sir, reply'd the Mareſchal <hi>de Lorge,</hi> the <hi>Germans</hi> go not ſo faſt in buſineſs; your Majeſty makes them gain at this time more Conqueſts, than they will make in three Campaigns.</p>
            <p>They are too great Friends to their Eaſe and good Cheer to forſake their Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Quarters in the Month of <hi>May.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I think on't <hi>de Lorge,</hi> ſays his Majeſty, How did you Govern your ſelf the laſt Campaign, which was that of 1691. for I hear that their Army was ſtrong.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>de Lorge,</hi> this Campaign was paſs'd like the reſt, that is to ſay, in diſputing the Ground. But as the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Army, commanded by the late Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> came very late into the Field, which is the Original Sin of the <hi>Germans,</hi> that of your Majeſty had two Months ſooner the Enemies Country at her diſcretion.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:175367:52"/>
            <p>After having caus'd the Forrage to be conſum'd on the Right and Left, as I had Orders from your Majeſty to keep my ſelf upon the Defenſive, I repaſs'd the <hi>Rhine</hi> upon the Arrival of the Enemies Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> pretended to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me; but as he wanted more neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries than I to make a Bridg, ſo I was on the other ſide before he was ready, and made my ſelf firſt Maſter of the beſt Poſts. The Marquiſs <hi>d <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xelles</hi> made on his ſide, with a Flying Camp, all the neceſſary Marches and Counter-marches, as well to cover the Place, as to give falſe Alarms to the Enemies. Monſieur <hi>de Melac</hi> open'd the Campaign by thirty Villages that he Burnt with a very good Grace. As he is the ableſt Incendiary of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſo he has reaſon to hope for a Mareſchals Staff for recompence.</p>
            <p>But, ſays his Majeſty, How did then the Deſigns of the Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> end?</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>de Lorge,</hi> this Elector was a good Prince, made much of by the God <hi>Mars,</hi> but a lover of Joy, of Pleaſure and of good Chear; Brave otherwiſe as the Sword he wore. But as he was not abſolute in the Army, and that I had the ſecret to divide them, I knew always be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:175367:52"/> by the means of my Spies and my Intelligence, all the Reſolutions taken in their Council: Beſides I do not know a Nation more lyable to be Corrupted than the <hi>Brabancons;</hi> at the ſight of a Golden Calf they all Humble and Proſtrate themſelves. St. <hi>Louis</hi> was a great Saint in <hi>Germany</hi> as well as in <hi>Flanders:</hi> I ſpeak as to particulars, becauſe as to the general, each People have their <hi>Scaevola,</hi> who had rather Dye a Thouſand times than betray their Country.</p>
            <p>To come back to my Subject, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion began, and the Sickneſs accompliſh'd the ruin of their Army, which coming to want Proviſions by the defect of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazines, ſaw themſelves reduc'd to the brink of falling into great extremities.</p>
            <p>The Elector himſelf having felt in his own Perſon part of the Evils, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to afflict his Army, went out of the Camp, and caus'd himſelf to be carryed, Sick of the Bloody Flux to <hi>Frankfort.</hi> Sometime after I heard of his Death, which made an end of the Expeditions of the Campaign of the <hi>Germans</hi> for the Year 1691.</p>
            <p>But, anſwer'd the King, that does not follow, and does not prove that it will be the ſame this year. The <hi>Germans</hi> may come
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:175367:53"/> again to themſelves, make juſt reflections, and enter into their true Intereſts; and as they have a mighty Spur, which is the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> and have on the other ſide from Forty to Fifty Thouſand Men; if they ſhould come all of a ſudden to paſs the <hi>Rhine</hi> and force you, I am perſwaded that you would be in a great confuſion, having but Ten Thouſand Men to oppoſe them. So that coming to loſe a Battle, I ſhould loſe the Faireſt Flower of my Crown, and my good Fortune, which has promis'd not to quit me but in the Grave, would bid me eternally Farewel. Beſides that, the <hi>Turk</hi> my Ally, whom I have till now ſtrove to raiſe up in his hopes, by the conſideration of the Progreſs that I have made upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> would turn his Back upon me, and making his ſeparate Peace with the Emperour our common Enemy, I ſhould find my ſelf in a very ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>de Lorge,</hi> do not forge unto your ſelf Monſters for fighting them. The Picture that your Majeſty now makes of the preſent State of <hi>Germany,</hi> is nothing leſs than ſuch. To be fully perſwaded therein we need reflect only upon what has been done on that ſide, ſince the beginning of the War till now.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:175367:53"/>
            <p>Three Campaigns are paſs'd without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gaind one Inch of Ground upon your Majeſty; and if the Deceaſed Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> whom we might have call'd with Juſtice the <hi>Turenne</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> had not by his Vigilance and his Bravery, ſtir'd up and animated the Electors to take the Reins in their Hands, and Unite all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to raiſe again the Glory of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, to work for her preſervation, and to ſet themſelves in oppoſition to the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Common Enemy, that ſame would not have been compaſſed. So that in the Campaign which was of 1689. we ſaw them beſtir themſelves, and minding their buſineſs heartily, they form'd the Siege of <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ence,</hi> of <hi>Bon</hi> and of <hi>Keiſerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wert,</hi> of which they made themſelves Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. But this great Zeal which had ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rongly animated them, cool'd by little and little, and was wholly ſtifled by the Death of him who had firſt rais'd it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>des, if your Majeſty wiſhes to have a more ſenſible proof of what your Enemies are in a condition to undertake on that ſide; you have only to follow the courſe of the <hi>Rhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> in beginning by the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> ſo to <hi>Coleg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and then to conſider the condition which moſt of the Members of the Empire
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:175367:54"/> have been reduc'd to ſince the Rupture of the Truce.</p>
            <p>Let us begin with the <hi>Palatinate:</hi> I do not think that your Majeſty has any thing to fear on that ſide, ſince it is only a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy remainder of what eſcap'd the Fury of the Soldiers, and the Barbarity of the Incendiaries, and by conſequence wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier of pity and compaſſion than to be fear'd.</p>
            <p>As for the Elector <hi>Palatine,</hi> he is a brave Prince, and who might be fear'd if he had Power in his Hands.</p>
            <p>Let us go on to the Elector of <hi>Mayence;</hi> neither will he put himſelf at the Head of the Imperial Army to Command it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe on the other ſide it is not his buſineſs. I am perſwaded that he will be very ſorry to have chang'd his Croſs for a Marſhal's Staff, and he ought long ago to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member'd the Allyance of your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and to have, more than he did, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken'd to the <hi>French</hi> Sirens, which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy hath made him become a Prince without Land, an Arch-biſhop without a Dioceſs, and a Shephard without a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lock, and he would have been ſtill in the ſame condition if the Deceaſed D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> and the Allies had not taken up Arms in his Favour, to recover him a part of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:175367:54"/> his Country; as for the reſt, the Charge of the War hath Eat it up, and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries have been in ſo great a deſolation, that they have ſtill need of Succour from the Emperor to preſerve them; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Majeſty has nothing to fear on that ſide.</p>
            <p>Let us ſpeak one word of the Elector of <hi>Treves;</hi> neither is War his buſineſs, and his Sword ſeems to me, never to have done hurt to any body. That does not hinder him to be one of the Braveſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Empire, but alſo one of the moſt unhappy, by the entire Deſolation of his Countries, which have felt the firſt Fury of the War, and ſaw themſelves ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the Violence of the Soldiers, the Walls of his Capital City layd even with the Ground, the Caſtle of his reſidence Batter'd with Cannon Shot, and <hi>Coblens</hi> overwhelm'd under a Shower of Bombs which have been thrown in at ſeveral times.</p>
            <p>As for the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter,</hi> he is ſo extreamly chang'd ſince the two firſt Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigns, that the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ies have no reaſon to depend upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him, nor upon his Troops, ſo that you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Majeſty has no reaſon neither to fear any thing from him, or that he for his part will come to trouble your— undertakings.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:175367:55"/>
            <p>As to what regards the Electorat of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logne,</hi> we may put them into the number of thoſe who have greatly ſuffered, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been the Seat of War all the time that the diſpute between the Cardinal <hi>de Furestemburgh</hi> and Prince <hi>Joſeph Clement</hi> remain'd undecided, and which was at laſt ended only by force of Arms, which had like to have overturn'd that State, and utterly to have ruin'd it. So that that Dioceſs will need many years quiet to repair her loſt forces and recover her ancient liberty.</p>
            <p>Be it as it will, the Prince <hi>Joſeph Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> is brave, and of whom there is great hopes; but on the other ſide he is too young to meaſure his Sword with your Majeſty; ſo you have no occaſion to fear any thing from that Quarter. From the Borders of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> let us go a little farther into the Country, and ſee if there is ſome new <hi>Caeſar</hi> which could carry the Glory of <hi>Germany</hi> ſo far, as did formerly that great Captain of the <hi>Romans;</hi> I would ſay a Prince a little reſolv'd, who ſhould come and put himſelf at the Head of the <hi>Germans,</hi> to ſerve them for a Sting, and animate them by his preſence.</p>
            <p>I only ſee the Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> who ſucceeds to that Electorſhip, vacant by
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:175367:55"/> the Death of the Elector his Father, and who ſeems to be engag'd to follow the Intereſt of the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> by reaſon of the ailyance of the Princeſs of <hi>Anſpach</hi> his Couſin, whom he has lately Married. But as he is a new Married Man, he will be glad to enjoy during the Summer the firſt ſweetneſs of his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, giving nevertheleſs the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his Troops to Monſieur <hi>Schoning</hi> our good Friend, heretofore in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and at preſent happily received and accepted General of the Troops of <hi>Saxony,</hi> ſo that your Majeſty has no more need to fear any thing on that ſide: One Countermarch may be of great uſe.</p>
            <p>But, ſays his Majeſty, you ſay nothing of the Electors of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> nor of the Princes of the Houſes of <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>over,</hi> who are notwithſtanding the Right Hand of all <hi>Germany,</hi> and who may when they think fit Form a Party to ballance all the Power of the Emperour, and of the other leſs potent Princes of the Empire.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>de Lorge,</hi> I do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to talk off the Electors of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> and <hi>Bavaria;</hi> and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch leſs of the Houſe of <hi>Hanover,</hi> becauſe theſe Princes having a greater ſhare in ſupporting the War of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:175367:56"/> 
               <hi>Flanders</hi> than that of <hi>Germany,</hi> ſince they have the greateſt part of their Troops in that Country, and that according to my judgment, they are reſolv'd to make ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great efforts, I leave the care to Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Luxemburgh</hi> to diſcourſe it throughly, being reſolv'd to meddle with nothing but the affairs of the <hi>Rhine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if your Majeſty deſires I ſhould ſpeak a word by the way, I will obey you wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and add to what has been ſaid of the Princes of the Empire, that to what relates to the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> we do not doubt but he is brave in his Perſon, and perhaps one of the greateſt Princes, that the Empire has yet produc'd; he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſignal marks in <hi>Hungary,</hi> where he has done for his Age, Actions worthy to be put in Paralell with what the boldeſt and moſt glorious Captains have done; I add to all that, that the Campaign of 1689. in which he Commanded with the late Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> the Army of the Confederates upon the <hi>Rhine;</hi> the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> to whom your Majeſty had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Command in Chief of your Army, had all the trouble imaginable, and was oblig'd to make uſe of all the tricks of War, to avoid a Battle; whilſt that his Brother-in-Law the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:175367:56"/> made on his ſide great Marches, and forc'd all that oppos'd his paſſage to come to engage; ſo far it is true that Hatred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes more and more irreconcileable when it is born amongſt Relations or Friends. But the failing of Generals, by the Death of two of the greateſt Captains of the Age, <hi>Lorrain</hi> and <hi>Schomberg,</hi> and the preſſing neceſſities that the Allies found themſelves in, by the progreſs that your Arms had made in <hi>Flanders, Savoy, Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia,</hi> and upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> was the cauſe that he went to Command in <hi>Italy,</hi> and from thence into <hi>Flanders,</hi> where he actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally is.</p>
            <p>It were only to be wiſh'd by them, that his Electoral Highneſs would uſe a little more Circumſpection in the choice he makes of his Domeſticks, and principally of his Muſicians, who wriggle themſelves into his Chappel, in the Habit of a Prieſt or Monk, not to ſay of a Fox, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to ſee what paſſes, and diſcover to his Enemies his moſt ſecret underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings; which is the greateſt misfortune that can happen to a General; and that he ought to endeavour to avoid as a plague capable to ſpoil all he does, to ruin his reputation, to make him unhappy, and baffle all his great deſigns.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:175367:57"/>
            <p>But it is an Univerſal Malady amongſt all the Allies; and there are very few of their Generals, who have yet found the ſecret to preſerve themſelves; and this is juſt the defect of their Breaſt-Plate, and by which your Majeſty carries even into the Heart your moſt formidable Blows, and that all the <hi>French</hi> Generals look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at this day, as the Seed of the Lawrels and Victories they have heap'd up one upon another. Your <hi>Majeſty</hi> may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from all that I have reported of the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> that this Prince will be for the future ſo ſtrongly employ'd in other places that I do not think we ſhall ſee him any more at the Head of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the <hi>Rhine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> ſays his Majeſty, could not he come in Perſon, for by what I can learn he is to make the Campaign, without being able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand where he is to Command.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwered <hi>de Lorge,</hi> I have told your Majeſty, and I'le repeat it again, that all theſe conſiderations ought not to ſtop the courſe of your Enterprizes. The Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> has to ſtreight En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements with the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to leave <hi>Brabant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe two Princes are inſeparable, and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:175367:57"/> will always hold together Mutually to maintain their Intereſts: It is not neceſſary I ſhould enlarge thereupon, nor that I ſhould ſearch Proofs at a diſtance; the Cataſtrophe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t happen'd in <hi>England,</hi> furniſhes a convincing Argument, and we may ſay, that this was the only Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor amongſt all the Members of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire to whom the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had open'd his Heart, and put confidence in.</p>
            <p>So the Elector on his ſide favour'd his deſign as well by his Troops, as by the Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hal <hi>de Schomberg,</hi> whom he off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d him with a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l freedom of Heart.</p>
            <p>So in <hi>Flanders,</hi> ſince the beginning of the War till now, and alſo during the time the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> labour'd in <hi>Ireland</hi> for the reduction of that Kingdom, the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor made it his chief Study to Act joyntly with Prince <hi>Waldeck,</hi> and we never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve ſeen him come back again to the <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> to quit the Command of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Troops which are almoſt all in the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vice of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I add alſo here, that I am perſwaded that your Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſty has loſt mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> by the Death of the late Elector his Father, if you conſider the free acceſs, and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty that he gave to your Miniſters,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:175367:58"/> who had thereby the occaſion to enter into the Cabinet of that Prince, to collect his moſt ſecret Thoughts; Monſieur <hi>de Rebenack</hi> knows it better than any one; but now it is no more ſo.</p>
            <p>The death of the late Electrice has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo depriv'd you of a good part of your beſt Intelligences, ſo that to renew them in this Court, you muſt implore the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of St. <hi>Louis,</hi> and beſtow behind the Curtain a good number of Piſtols, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which your Majeſty will be Maſter of the Secrets there, as you are in all other places.</p>
            <p>But, anſwer'd his Majeſty, as to matter of Intelligence, I juſt now learn'd with a great deal of regret, and alſo with ſome kind of trouble, that the poor General <hi>Schoning</hi> was arreſted by order of the Emperor, and carry'd to <hi>Spielberg</hi> in <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia</hi> where he is Condemned to a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual priſon. That troubles me ſo much the more, becauſe I loſe in him one of the moſt faithful Correſpondents that I had in all <hi>Germany,</hi> and in one word a ſecond <hi>Fuſtemberg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall never forget the Obligation I have to him, and the Siege of <hi>Bon,</hi> where he found the Means to make it hold out five whole Months after it was Bombar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:175367:58"/> which was of great help to me, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſe the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> the whole Campaign.</p>
            <p>If the good Man had been believ'd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Affairs would have fallen'n well out.</p>
            <p>Sir, your Majeſty will never fail of Spies, if you do but largely reward them. Money has charms whoſe Brightneſs dazle a Man's Reaſon, and makes all things to be undertaken; and if your Enemies had this ſecret, your Majeſty would not reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo many Victories nor Conqueſts: But their parcimony has ſerv'd more to bring your Majeſty to the Period whither you are at preſent come, than your great and numerous Armies.</p>
            <p>A Secret Bought is worth a Battle won, and a Governour corrupted is worth the Conqueſt of an Important City. So I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you to keep your ſelf alway<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at the Trunk of a Tree, in following ſtep by ſtep the Tracts of <hi>Richiieu</hi> and <hi>Mazarine,</hi> who have ſo worthily inſtructed you, in tracing their ways to come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the end of your undertakings, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> come at laſt to the Univerſal Monarc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Cent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of all your Glori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ings.</p>
            <p>As to the matter of Monarchy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d his Majeſty, ſay what you t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nk of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:175367:59"/> Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Hanover,</hi> and let us make an end of talking of the Affairs of <hi>Germany,</hi> with the Chief of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</p>
            <p>As to what regards, ſays <hi>de Lorge,</hi> the Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Hanover,</hi> your Majeſty has had even to this time no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to complain of their Hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>They love Tranquility too well, to fear they ſhould come to put themſelves at the Head of the <hi>Germans,</hi> to paſs the <hi>Rhine</hi> Headlong, and for the Glory of the Nation hazard a Battle. As to their Troops which are the fineſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> has found the means to engage them in his ſervice, in making the Emperour agree, that the Eldeſt Duke of the Family ſhould augment the number of Electors, and that he ſhould be receiv'd into the Electoral Colledge. Which ſhews that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is look'd upon at preſent, as the Star that Governs in the World, and that he has only to deſire in order to obtain.</p>
            <p>Prerogatives of a Prince, which he hath acquired, without thinking of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Monarchy, to which your Majeſty has aſpir'd, ſince ſo many years, and for which you have ſo mercileſly caus'd ſo
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:175367:59"/> much Blood to be ſpilt, and ſo many States, and Provinces to be overthrown, and ſo many People to be ruin'd, whilſt this Prince Arrives by the way of Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and complacency— and by gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Friendſhip of the People, who regard him already as their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer, and another <hi>Joſhua,</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſtop the<note n="*" place="margin">The King of <hi>France.</hi>
               </note> Sun in the midſt of his courſe</p>
            <p>I forgot to tell you, ſays his Majeſty, that my Agent <hi>Bidal</hi> has let me know that the Landgrave of <hi>Heſse, Caſſel,</hi> and the Margrave <hi>de Bareith</hi> are to Command the Armies of the Confederates upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> ſo you will have occaſion of a great deal of management; I recommend to to you above all to avoid a Battle.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>de Lorge,</hi> reſt ſatisfied there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, if they are two, I have the ſecret in Hand to divide them, and I promiſe my ſelf before-hand with my ſmall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber a glorious Campaign.</p>
            <p>But, ſays his Majeſty, do you know well the Landgrave <hi>de Heſſel Caſſel?</hi> do you know that he and the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> are two Heads in one Cap, that he is brave in his Perſon, and that he is to be fear'd?</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>de Lorge,</hi> yes if he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:175367:60"/> but it is ſufficient they are two to Command, and by conſequence two Heads, of which each will have his Counſellors; reſt ſatisfied that I will accompliſh it, <hi>alios vidimus ventos,</hi> ſays <hi>Virgil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have ſeen other Outrages and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, and it is no new thing that we fight againſt two Chiefs. We do not ſee Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Wiſdom divided and parted, in all the parts of Human Body, but ſhee reſides, and has her principal Seat in the Brain of a Man.</p>
            <p>A Body which ſhould have two Souls, would be depriv'd of this agreeable Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny which produces health, and which cauſes all the parts that compoſe it to Act in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. It is the ſame with an Army, which is Commanded by two Generals. It is impoſſible they ſhould be free from divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is more pernicious than the loſs of Battles.</p>
            <p>Beſides <hi>de Lorge,</hi> ſays his Majeſty, if the Emperour <hi>Leopold</hi> ſtirr'd up by my Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, or by Imitation of the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, his Predeceſſors, ſhould of a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den take the reſolution to come himſelf at the Head of the Army upon the <hi>Rhine</hi> to govern it, and ſee what paſſes there, I muſt own I ſhould be in a great deal of trouble upon this account, and that you
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:175367:60"/> would be in no leſs than I, becauſe I am perſwaded that the preſence of a Prince, who ſhews and expoſes himſelf to danger in ſight of his Soldiers, and of his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, is a mighty Example. If the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperour my Allie, would have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd me, and have hearken'd to my Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour the Baron <hi>de Chaſteau Neuf,</hi> he would have come in Perſon to have put himſelf at the Head of his Armies in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> I doubt not but he would thereby have preſerv'd all his Conqueſts, carryed the dread for the ſecond time to the Gates of <hi>Vienna,</hi> and ſav'd many Battles, loſt by the fault of his <hi>Viziers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd the Duke <hi>de Lorge,</hi> the Emperour <hi>Leopold</hi> and his Nephew <hi>Charles</hi> the II. King of <hi>Spain</hi> are not ſo Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious as your Majeſty. Theſe are two good Princes, who ſeek only Repoſe and Peace, and ſhun the Cruelties of the War. And if your Majeſty had not conſtrain'd them to take up Arms to maintain their Intereſts, and thoſe of all <hi>Europe,</hi> they would not have troubled themſelves at this time to go and gather Lawrels in the Field of <hi>Mars;</hi> this God doth not Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathize with thoſe Princes; <hi>Apollo</hi> has ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Charms, and Mount <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> other Enchantments. Formerly <hi>Orpheus</hi>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:175367:61"/> by the ſweetneſs of Inſtruments drew to him all the Beaſts; and alſo the inſenſible Creatures, the Rocks and the Woods could not defend themſelves from his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive Harmony. It is true, that if <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemaigne, Charles</hi> the V. and <hi>Phillip</hi> the II. ſhould come from the other World, this reproach would without doubt be made them. But every Prince has his Paſſions, his Inclinations, and his Weakneſſes; your Majeſty loves War, the late King <hi>Charls</hi> the II. King of <hi>England</hi> lov'd the fair Sex, and your Majeſty took care to make him a Preſent of Miſtreſſes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor loves a Harmony; make him a Preſent of Muſicians, and they will take care to inform you of all that paſſes at the Court of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I underſtand alſo Sir, that the Electors at preſent, for the moſt part, Study the Inclinations of their Prince, and ſtrive to imitate him in all things, which is the reaſon they are all almoſt lovers of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick. So there remains no more for your Majeſty to do, than to make a proviſion of Muſicians, (<hi>Brabant</hi> above all abounds of ſuch) and ſend them into all the Courts of <hi>Germany,</hi> and this will be a Sovereign remedy to know and diſcover all.</p>
            <p>What I have juſt now ſaid furniſhes me
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:175367:61"/> yet with one thought, which is, that it is not to be wonder'd at (as a politick <hi>Spaniard</hi> did once very judiciouſly ſay) that your Majeſty has ſurpas'd <hi>Henry</hi> the IV. <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIII. and in a word all your predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, by a great number of events, which have happn'd during your Reign, and which are ſolely owing to the Wiſdom, and to the good fortune of your Majeſty, ſince we ſee that the Imbecility of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who have Reign'd in your time, have as much, and alſo more contributed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. If you had had for Competitors, Queen <hi>Elizabeth, Guſtavus Adolphus,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> the V. which would have diſputed the Ground with you; as you had <hi>Charles</hi> the II. and <hi>James</hi> the II. Kings of <hi>England</hi> the Emperour <hi>Leopold,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> the II. King of <hi>Spain,</hi> who have let you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take any thing, I am perſwaded you would not have got ſo many Victories. But this is the unhappy condition of States. The downfal of one is the riſe of the other. I ſay alſo farther; if it ſhould happen, by way of fatality, as we may ſay, that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was not met with in your Reign, and alſo that being met with, he had not been animated with another Zeal than the reſt of the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> for the defence of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:175367:62"/> and the preſervation of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, all would long ſince have fallen under the weight of your Arms, and your Majeſty would have finiſhed the great Work of the Univerſal Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy.</p>
            <p>But, ſays his Majeſty, what do you hear of the Negotiation of the Peace between the two Empires? Monſieur <hi>Harbord</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> has he been well receiv'd by the <hi>Grand Vizier?</hi> I know the enterview was to be at <hi>Belgrade,</hi> what have you learnt, and what are your thoughts thereupon? Do you believe that he will ſucceed better than Penſionary <hi>Hop</hi> and the Knight <hi>Huſſey</hi> have done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore?</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>de Lorge,</hi> I know from good Hands that the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes for a Peace, and that the People will have it at any rate; ſo your Majeſty has no more time to loſe, and there wants but one moment to conclude it, and to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile theſe two Powers. The <hi>French</hi> Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens who are at the Court of the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> begin to looſe a little of the Charms of their Singing and their Melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as well as their credit. The <hi>Louis d' Ors</hi> are ſo ſtrongly cry'd down at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> that no Body will have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:175367:62"/> more to do with them.</p>
            <p>I adviſe then your Majeſty to puſh on your great deſigns; the time preſſes, prevent your Enemy in the Field; your Majeſty being at the Head of a flouriſhing Army, may go fall on where you think fit, and carry one of the ſtrongeſt places of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I adviſe you again to make your laſt efforts, to come to a Peace, an to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the concluſion of the Truce between the two Emperours, and if Mony is not capable to hinder it, to employ yet more Sovereign remedies, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Harbord</hi> poyſoned.</note> 
               <hi>Brinvilliers</hi> in the Hands of a <hi>French</hi> Cook are infallible.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the Mareſchal <hi>de Lorge,</hi> was gone out of the Chamber, the King or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd that the Count <hi>de Tourville</hi> and <hi>John Barts</hi> ſhould come in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tourville,</hi> ſaies his Majeſty, I have two great deſigns in hand, and I have choſe you to execute the one, whilſt I am going to execute the other at the Head of an Army, of one Hundred and Fifty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men. There is no time to loſe, the occaſion is preſſing, and the reſolution is taken.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I propoſe to my ſelf to re-eſtabliſh
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:175367:63"/> King <hi>James</hi> upon the Throne of <hi>England:</hi> And in the ſecond place to conſtrain my Enemies, who have flatter'd themſelves to ſtop the Courſe of my Conqueſts, to ask for a Peace.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Tourville,</hi> nothing is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for your Majeſty; you have a formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Fleet which makes you Maſter of the Sea, &amp; which obliges your Enemies to yield you that Empire, for which ſo many Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have ſpilt their Blood.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> boaſted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves till now to poſſeſs it, but the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fight of 1690. has decided it to the advantage of your Majeſty, ſo you are in a condition to undertake all that you pleaſe on that ſide. By Land your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty is no leſs formidable, you have great and Valiant Armies, always ready for the execution of your vaſt undertakings; you have able Generals to Command them, who Work for nothing but the Glory of their Prince; and which is more, you have the Philoſopher's Stone in your Hand, that is to ſay, the ſecret to draw from your Subjects what Mony you pleaſe, which renders you formidable to all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> and makes you always Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant.</p>
            <p>That's not the matter in hand, ſays his
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:175367:63"/> Majeſty, I well know that I am fear'd, by my Enemies; but by land I have more reaſon to truſt to the good fortune of my Arms than by Sea. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ſeem to me yet to be fear'd, if a good underſtanding ſhould once come to Reign amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Tourville,</hi> if your Majeſty takes the pains to run over the Hiſtory of your Reign, you will ſee many Victories that your Admirals have gain'd upon the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> who are alſo yet as much to be fear'd as the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> becauſe beſides the method they have of blowing up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves rather than ſubmit, they alſo other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe fight like mad-men. But let it be as it will, there has been ſeveral Fights du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this reign, the chiefeſt of which was that of <hi>Tobago,</hi> where the Mareſchal <hi>d' Eſtre</hi> Sunk almoſt all the <hi>Holland</hi> Fleet; there have been alſo many others that Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>du Queſne</hi> had upon the Coaſts of <hi>Sicily,</hi> in one of which the famous <hi>Ruyter,</hi> Admiral of <hi>Holland,</hi> was kill'd, which was a very ſenſible and irreparable loſs for that Republick, and which ſhe felt many years after. In another Fight all the Enemies Fleet was burnt under the Canon of <hi>Palermo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, ſays his Majeſty, all thoſe times are
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:175367:64"/> paſt, and experience has ſhewn me in the year 1690. when you fought againſt the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> which were in all but Twenty Four great Men of War, whereas you had Eighty Five, that you had nevertheleſs a great deal of trouble with that great number to draw your ſelf off from the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement; and I do not know whether my Fleet was more damag'd than theirs; ſince you brought no other mark of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, than that of carrying back to <hi>Breſt</hi> my Ships much diſabled without having taken from the Enemies one ſimple Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loop.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Tourville,</hi> I vow to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, that my ſurprize was great to ſee ſo ſmall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> number reſiſt and fight againſt a Fleet whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h we had reaſon to take for Invincible, and I much doubt if that of <hi>Philip</hi> the II. which was ſo called when ſhe went to the Conqueſt of three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, was ſo Fine, ſo Formidable, and ſo Numerous in great Ships of War.</p>
            <p>Be it as it will, Sir, generally all the Fleet of your Majeſty, fought againſt this ſmall number, Monſieur <hi>de Gabaret</hi> had like to have been taken off with a Canon Bullet, and had more than Two Hundred kill'd aboard. Monſieur <hi>de Neſmo d</hi> did wonderfully well, but his Ship <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as ſo
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:175367:64"/> maul'd, that we had a great deal of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to carry her off. Monſieur the Count <hi>d' Eſtre</hi> was Wounded in the Leg by a Splinter, and had a great number kill'd and wounded aboard. The Marqueſs <hi>de la Porte</hi> came off at no cheaper a rate than the Count <hi>d' Eſtre,</hi> and his Ship was greatly damaged.</p>
            <p>The Marquis <hi>de Vallette</hi> was obliged to Change his Ship, ſo much had ſhe been ſhot through and through; he had above half his Equipage kill'd without reckoning the wounded. In ſhort, Sir, what I Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port here to your Majeſty is but an abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the loſſes we had, and I content my ſelf to ſpeak of the Admirals and Chiefs of Squadrons, paſſing over in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence a great number of Officers of leſs conſiderable Ships. But as to the reſt your Majeſty had the glory of the Fight and the Victory on your ſide.</p>
            <p>But that is not all, ſays his Majeſty, you will have a ſtronger Enemy to fight with this Campaign, than the former, if I may believe my Spies in <hi>Holland,</hi> and chiefly at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> who have let me know poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, that that Republick has reſolv'd to put to Sea for her <hi>quota,</hi> a Fleet of Forty five great Ships, which being joyn'd to Fifty that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> will furniſh, will
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:175367:65"/> make a very potent Fleet; ſo I have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to preſage quite another Event, and if it ſhould happen by misfortune that you ſhould be beaten you will ruin all my undertakings.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Tourville,</hi> if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lookers on, as there is all appearance, I have the Victory in my Pocket.</p>
            <p>But do you know well, ſays his Majeſty, that the <hi>Holl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nders</hi> alone are almoſt as ſtrong in number as you will be?</p>
            <p>Sir, it is no matter, ſays <hi>Tourville,</hi> the Naval Army of your Majeſty, if actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of Forty Four great Ships, without reckoning the Six, which are yet at <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk,</hi> and the fourteen th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the Count <hi>d' Estre</hi> brings from <hi>Toulon,</hi> the which joyn'd together, will make a Fleet more than ſufficient to beat the Enemy, tho' the two Nations together ſhould fight their beſt. I ſuppoſe alſo the advantage, that if it ſhould happen by a misfortune, or by contrary Winds, that Monſieur <hi>d' Eſtre</hi> was not in a condition to joyn me, Sir I engage at the Peril of my Life, to go and attack them with the Forty Four which compoſes the main of the Fleet, and which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more, to come back Glorious and Triumphant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tourville,</hi> ſays his Majeſty, have a care,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:175367:65"/> who reckons without his Enemy reckons twice; <hi>Mazarine</hi> always told me, in my Youth, That Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight and Wiſdom made the firſt degree of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of the great ones; and that a Prince who did not foreſee the Misfortunes which might happen to him, was not worthy to Reign. So I have always ſo ſtrongly ſtrove to follow the Maxims of that good Man, that I would never hazard any thing; and I have found my ſelf very well ſatisfied with it. So I have order'd all my Generals, upon pain of Death, not to hazard a Battle, unleſs they were aſſured of the Victory.</p>
            <p>To make ſhort then, <hi>Tourville,</hi> free you ſeem to have Courage enough, here is the order you muſt keep in attacking my Enemies.</p>
            <p>Having ranged my Fleet in Batalia, you muſt go ſtreight upon them, and you muſt Poſt your ſelf op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>te and in preſence of the <hi>Engliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> after having <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured"
                    resp="#KEYERS"
                    extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>g up the red Flag, you muſt ſalute A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miral <hi>Ruſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el</hi> very civilly with two broad-ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s of Canon, only with Powder, and without Ball: after this Salvo, and one moment after, you muſt make Sign to all my Fleet to do the ſame, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that with Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, in imitating you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>remony being done, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured"
                    resp="#KEYERS"
                    extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>u will know immed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ately if A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miral <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured"
                    resp="#KEYERS"
                    extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th the Matter. For if I may believe K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes,</hi> the V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctory is ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s: and at this Signal all the <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> will range themſelves on my ſide and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured"
                    resp="#KEYERS"
                    extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>in you. This Prelude being plaid, you muſt make <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured"
                    resp="#KEYERS"
                    extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>alf a turn to the left, and you muſt go Poſt your ſelf ſtrait in the preſence of the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> who you muſt vigorouſly attack with my whole Fleet: and as after the joining of the <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gliſh</hi> Fleet, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u will be ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onger by half than they, I flatter my ſelf already, beforehand, that you will obtain one of the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt ſignalized Victories which has y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t been gain'd. I recommend to you, above all, to be I exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ble,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:175367:66"/> and to deſtroy without Pity and without Mercy, my Enemies, to exterminate them, and to act ſo that not one eſcape.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tourville,</hi> call to your remembrance the Fight of 1690. and ſee that that happens no more to you, to let the <hi>Hollanders</hi> retire, without taking one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Bark from them.</p>
            <p>Whilſt you ſhall be engag'd, King <hi>James</hi> ſhall be upon the Coaſt to judge of the Blows, waiting for the Event; and the Deſcent into <hi>England</hi> will follow immediately after, and all that without loſing time.</p>
            <p>The King ask'd for <hi>John Barts,</hi> who was retir'd out of the way: <hi>John Barts</hi> ſeeing his Majeſty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd to ſpeak with him, anſwered Sir, I am here.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Barts,</hi> ſays his Majeſty, how go the Prizes? Do you take many of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Hollanders?</hi> For by what I can learn, theſe two Nations fear you.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwered <hi>John Barts,</hi> I have reſolv'd, ſaving your Majeſty's good pleaſure, to carry the <hi>French</hi> Piracy to ſo high a degree, that all the Capers of <hi>France</hi> ſhall have reaſon to call me their Father, their Patron and their Reſtorer; and, finally, after my death, thoſe of S. <hi>Malo</hi> and <hi>Dunkirk</hi> ſhall can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonize me in Memory of my great Actions, and my name plac'd in the Kalendar, ſhall be named, <hi>The Feaſt of</hi> John Barts <hi>the holy Thief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, I hope, by the help of the Almighty, to out-do quickly, by my Tricks and my good Prizes, all that has been formerly moſt boldly done by the <hi>Mezomortes</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Tripoly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, anſwer'd his Majeſty, if it ſhould happen that you ſhould fall into the Hands of your Enemies, I am perſuaded that they would make you paſs your time very ill.</p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:175367:66"/>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>John Barts,</hi> I fear nothing ſo much as the <hi>Zealand</hi> Capers, formerly my joint Brothers, and at preſent my mortal Enemies, becauſe they are ſo angry that I have betray'd my Country and their Party, to embrace that of your Majeſty's, that they will call me in their Language, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rede Breeker,</hi> Breaker of the Peace, that they would never par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me; beſides, they cannot indure that I ſhould ſurpaſs them in Malice, and that I ſhould teach the <hi>French</hi> their Art, of which they are jealous even to the laſt degree.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Barts,</hi> ſays his Majeſty, this is not all; I have two great Deſigns in hand, the one in <hi>Flanders</hi> and the other in <hi>England,</hi> and I ſee my ſelf juſt upon the point of Execution, and to make it ſucceed, I ſhall have occaſion for all my Forces by Sea and Land; ſo it is, and for that end I have call'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all my Generals to take their Advice, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct this Enterprize with all the Prudence imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. My deſign is, then, to go into <hi>Flanders,</hi> at the Head of an Army of 150000 Men, and to form the Siege of the ſtrongeſt place of <hi>Europe;</hi> whilſt I ſhall be buſy in the execution of it, you muſt get together all my Capers and form a Fleet, of which I make you, from this time, Admiral, in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of your good Services; and you muſt act on one ſide, whilſt the Count <hi>de Tourville</hi> ſhall act on the other, according to the Orders I have given him; and you muſt make your Movements and your Courſes, with your flying Camp of Pirates, being well ſettled in Concert and Intelligence with <hi>Tourville:</hi> As to the reſt, I recommend to you the Secret.</p>
            <p>Aſſoon as the Count <hi>de Tourville</hi> and <hi>John Barts</hi> were gone out, his Majeſty order d, That Monſieur <hi>de Pompone</hi> ſhould come.</p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:175367:67"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pompone,</hi> ſays the King, I recommend to you my Kingdom, I am juſt upon my departure, the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions are taken, and I am to be in <hi>Flanders</hi> at the Head of 150000 Men; ſo I leave you the Reins of Government, during my abſence. You are the wiſeſt of my Miniſters, and after the death of poor <hi>Louvois,</hi> I knew not how to make choice of a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier Subject than you. Father <hi>La Chaize,</hi> my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, is not contented; and the old Quarrels that theſe good Fathers have had, with your Uncle Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Arnaud,</hi> run ſtill in their Heads.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Pompone,</hi> the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> will always flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in your Kingdom in ſpight of the Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Society, and of their violent Prejudices againſt them. I know what I have ſuffered upon their account, having try'd many Storms, which had made me reſolve upon a voluntary Baniſhment, in retireing into the Country, to be ſecure from their Perſecution and their Rage; Monſieur <hi>de Louvois</hi> neither was none of my beſt Friends; he had too much correſpondence with Father <hi>la Chaize,</hi> not to join Forces and attempt my Ruin every way he could; but without ranſaking the Aſhes of the dead, I rejoyce to ſee my Innocence applauded by the confidence your Majeſty repoſes in me concerning the Affairs of your Kingdom.</p>
            <p>As you have been, ſays his Majeſty, in Ambaſſy in <hi>Holland,</hi> and that you know perfectly the Genius and Intereſt of that Republick, I have but one word to ſay to you, to make you apprehend imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately what is my end, in going to the Head of my Armies; it is one Home-puſh for the Game, and the only one to come to a Peace; <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> made me ſee it as clear as the day.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Pompone,</hi> it is high time for your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to begin to ſet bounds to your Ambition, and that you cheriſh your People; the whole Kingdom
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:175367:67"/> is oppreſs'd, and groans under the heavy Burden of Impoſts and Subſidies, and therefore 'tis dangerous for ſo great a Prince as you, to expoſe himſelf too much.</p>
            <p>If the Preſence of your Majeſty is neceſſary in your Army, it is no leſs ſo in your Kingdom, where you ſupport your Power and Sovereignty, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipate the Plots of the Malecontents; which keeps Proſperity among your People, and preſerves the Harmony that is neceſſary between him that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and thoſe that obey.</p>
            <p>We have experienc'd in all Ages paſt, that thoſe Kings who have ſtaid at home in their Cloſets have executed greater things, than thoſe have done, whom Ambition and an inſatiable deſire of Glory have carried even to the extremities of the World. <hi>Charles</hi> V. and <hi>Louis</hi> XI. have atchiev'd greater Exploits, without going out of their Palace, than did <hi>Louis</hi> the Young and <hi>Philip</hi> the Auguſt, in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Seas, and in carrying their Arms into <hi>Africa;</hi> we ſtill feel the ſmart of what was occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in <hi>France,</hi> by the Impriſonment of St. <hi>Louis,</hi> of King <hi>John,</hi> and of <hi>Francis</hi> I. Sir, theſe are Wounds to the State, and irreparable Loſſes when they happ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pompone,</hi> ſays his Majeſty, the Reſolution is taken, and the Dice is thrown; this Campaign will be no more dangerous for my Perſon, than that of <hi>Mons</hi> was, and ſo many others that I have made in my Reign; Fortune cheriſhes me too much, to leave me now I am in ſo fair a Career.</p>
            <p>A King is never Great nor Illuſtrious, who has not carried his Arms among Strangers to make them know his Strength, and to make them feel the ſweetneſs and equity of his Commands. I had all my Life an averſion for thoſe ſlothful Kings of the firſt Race, who did not govern their Countries, but
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:175367:68"/> ſuffer'd themſelves to be govern'd by the Grandees; nothing is more pernicious to a Prince, than Luxury and too much Repoſe. <hi>Nero,</hi> whoſe firſt years were ſo admirable and ſo great, eclips'd the luſtre of them by his Debau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hes and his Cruelties, which were but the fatal conſequence or Idleneſs.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Pompone,</hi> if your Majeſty has ſo conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uded, and that you think it fit, for the way to a Peace, I wiſh you all Proſperity and a happy Campaign.</p>
            <p>The time of my departure draws near, ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his Majeſty; I recommend to you, above all, to have an Eye upon the <hi>new Catholicks,</hi> whom I look upon, in my Abſence, as Enemies moſt to be fear'd. You know what care I have taken to bring them back to the boſom of the Church, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how I have b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en forc'd to uſe them, to pluck up this curſed Tare which has mix'd it ſelf with the good Corn.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Pomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne,</hi> I do not know, if your Majeſty had all the reaſon in the World to deliver them ſo mercileſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y to the reſentment of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; for my pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ticular, I felt a part of their Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, and Father <hi>la Chaiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> gave me no better Quarters than them.</p>
            <p>Your Illuſtrious Predeceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, witneſs the Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father of your Majeſty, <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n y</hi> IV. came to the Crown only by their a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſiſtance. They did h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m ſo great Services, when he ſaw himſelf overwhelm'd by the <hi>Cath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ks,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a conſiderable Party, ca <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e League,</hi> that he woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly ſunk with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut their Aſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tance; ſo, in memory of their Fidelity, he gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted them the <hi>Edict of</hi> Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s. So that your Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſty ought to conſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, that if you have, at this day, the Crown upon y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Head, as a moſt worthy Succeſſor of that Great <hi>Henry,</hi> you are no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs beholding to them than your Grandfather.</p>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:175367:68"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pompone,</hi> ſays his Majeſty, let us talk of other things. It ſuffices to tell you, That the G <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured"
                    resp="#KEYERS"
                    extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ence, having ſo order'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it, it was no longer in my Power to oppoſe it. In ſhort, I am going, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therefore recommend to you, abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e all my Kingdom, my new Converts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I recommend to you the Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een of <hi>Great B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itain,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Infant of <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> land,</hi> viſit them often and comfort them in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſgrace; te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them, from me, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t I go where Glory calls me, to heap up Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to accomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſh their re-eſtab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſhment.</p>
            <p>I rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſo to you my S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uphi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured"
                       resp="#KEYERS"
                       extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> take care above all, to repreſent to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m the Inj ry he does to his Reputation, to love rather the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Diana</hi> and the Hunting of the Wolf than the noble Works of <hi>Mars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I recommend to you alſo the three young Princes, my Grand-children; entertain them, above all, with the great Actions of their Grand-father; I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to you chiefly the Eldeſt, the Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> whom I us'd to call the Prince of <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de;</hi> becauſe that truly we ſee, as it were reb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rn in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m all the ſhining Qualities of that Prince.</p>
            <p>I recommend to you, in ſhort, all the Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences that I have in Foreign Courts, have a care of them: receive the Letters that ſhall be writ to me, and cauſe the Sums deſign'd for the Penſions I pay them, to be return'd. I alſo very carefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to you my Treaſury; aſſiſt <hi>Ponchart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aine</hi> with your good Advice, and lend him your Hand in working jointly for ſettling a Fund for the next Campaign.</p>
            <p>Mony is the Sinew of War, without it I ſhould be a K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thout Power, and all my great Deſigns would evaporate int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>moak.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Pompone,</hi> they report of <hi>Dag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bert,</hi> that he was ſo j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt and free towards the Churches, That
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:175367:69"/> he caus'd the Church of St. <hi>Dennis</hi> to be covered with Silver. But your Majeſty makes another uſe of Mony, you have a quite different Pity and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice from that Prince. You imitate rather him, who finding the 12 Apoſtles of Maſſy Silver in a Church, caus'd them to be taken from the Altar; and having made them into Mony, told them, That they ſhould go Preach, throughout the whole World, according to the order that <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> had given them.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>de Pompone</hi> being gone out, the King or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, that Meſſieurs <hi>de Barbeſieux</hi> and <hi>de Chanlais</hi> ſhould come in in all haſte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Barbeſieux,</hi> ſays his Majeſty, the Reſolutions are taken; I have a great Deſign in hand: Silence, we are now at the point to bring great things to Light; the Campaign of <hi>Mons</hi> had nothing like it.</p>
            <p>Ha! what then! Sir, ſays <hi>Barbeſieux.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am a going, ſays his Majeſty, into <hi>Flanders,</hi> at the Head of an Army of 150000 Men, to form the Siege of the Key of all the Low Countries.: <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emburgh</hi> has ſhou'd it me as clear as the Sun at Noon.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Chanlais,</hi> your Majeſty muſt make haſte, for I hear that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> will come a Month ſooner into the Field than he did laſt year.</p>
            <p>It is no matter, ſays his Majeſty, I ſhall have near 80000 Men more than he, and I ſhall be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by three potent Armies; beſides, I will make <hi>Boufflers</hi> go before and poſſeſs himſelf of the Paſſages. <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> has aſſur'd me, that I have no more cauſe to fear, than if I were at <hi>Verſailles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd <hi>Barbeſieux,</hi> if that be ſo, your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will have a good Bargain for all you ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, whilſt that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> fatigues and expoſes himſelf to the moſt eminent Dangers.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Chanlais,</hi> Gold and Treaſon are at this day two great double Keys to your Majeſty; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:175367:69"/> that they open all Gates, they operate more in a moment than great Armies do in a Summer's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition.</p>
            <p>Both the one and the other muſt be had, ſays his Majeſty; I have found out the means to tame the Lion and the Fox, which were heretofore incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible, and I only march now to take Poſſeſſion of what I have bought before.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Barbeſieux,</hi> that is not all; your Majeſty muſt ſeek the ſhorteſt way to come quickly to a Peace; the want of every thing is a dangerous Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, which begins to be felt throughout your Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Barbeſieux,</hi> you ſpeak home, ſays his Majeſty, and all the advantage I propoſe to my ſelf, by this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, is to come to the way of a Peace.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Barbeſieux,</hi> I have yet a ſhorter way, and more abridg'd than that, to come to a Peace.</p>
            <p>Ha! what? ſays his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>It is to put in execution the Project that my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Father, the Marquiſs <hi>de Louvois,</hi> had begun the rough draught of, and which he left in his Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net after his death; that is, the White that is the Center whereto all your Majeſty's Enterprizes ſhould tend.</p>
            <p>What muſt be done then, ſays his Majeſty?</p>
            <p>Sir, the Buſineſs in hand, is to ſend the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> Chief of the League, <hi>ad Patres,</hi> if your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will conſent to it. It is he that ſits at the Helm, and is the chiefeſt Promoter of this War, who draws by his Rapidity, the Princes and the Circles of the Empire, as well as the other States at preſent in War with your Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Sir, added <hi>Chanlais,</hi> thereby King <hi>James</hi> will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount his Throne immediately, and your Majeſty will impoſe what Laws you pleaſe to the Allies, who then would ſee themſelves without a Head, and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:175367:70"/> would be like a Flock without a Shepherd. The Dogs of <hi>England</hi> coming to fail, the Wolf would enter into the Park, ſacrificing all to her rage, without Pity and without Mercy.</p>
            <p>But, ſays his Majeſty, how can that be? Such an Undertaking gives me Horror.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Barbeſieux,</hi> that's not the matter in hand; your Majeſty is in the Mire, as we ſay, you muſt draw your ſelf out of it coſt what it will.</p>
            <p>But good God, ſays his Majeſty, if the World ſhould come to know that I had conſented to ſo black an Attempt, what would they ſay of me?</p>
            <p>When I ſhall have throughly acquainted your Majeſty, ſays <hi>Barbeſieux,</hi> with the Importance of the Project and the eaſineſs of the Execution, we will look out for Remedies to cure the niceneſs of your Conſcience.</p>
            <p>What is your Opinion of it, then, ſays his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty?</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Barbeſieux,</hi> I have two profligate Men ready, <hi>Grandvall</hi> and <hi>Dumont,</hi> who ſhall be the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakers of this glorious Tragedy; I will charge my ſelf with the Event, and will anſwer for the Succeſs.</p>
            <p>Ho! ho! ſays his Majeſty, you have then your People ready.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Barbeſieux,</hi> the late Marquiſs <hi>de Louvois,</hi> my Father, has been ſo happy as to do your Majeſty ſome conſiderable Services, during your Reign, and he would have added this to the reſt of his good Deeds, if Death had not cut him off; but having ſnatch'd him out of the World, when he thought the leaſt of it, he charg'd me, as his worthy Son, to proceed to the execution of his laſt Will, and to be Aſſiſtant to this great Work.</p>
            <p>Ha, ha, ſays his Majeſty, <hi>Louvois</hi> had then under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken it, had he? I ſhould never have thought that of him.</p>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:175367:70"/>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Barbeſieux,</hi> is your Majeſty ignorant then, that the death of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and now of late, the Knight <hi>Harboard,</hi> hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by our means, with the help of a little Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? We have brought the Affairs of the War on the <hi>Rhine</hi> into a good Poſture, and caus'd, on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, all the Propoſitions of Peace to vaniſh, that the <hi>Turk,</hi> your Ally, made to the Emperor. No Sir, that your Majeſty may not flatter your ſelf, you owe all to Poyſon, to Mony and to Treaſon; and if you had not on your ſide theſe great and mighty Springs, you would never with all your numerous Armies, have puſhed on your Frontiers ſo far.</p>
            <p>Let us ſpeak ſoftly, ſays his Majeſty, for fear ſome of my Enemies ſhould be here; I would not for a hundred ſuch Crowns as I wear, this ſhould come to the Ears of the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, added <hi>Chanlais,</hi> your Majeſty muſt know, That there is no Prince in the World who marches with more freedom and ſimplicity, than the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> He expoſes himſelf to Danger without troubling himſelf about the Event; Predeſtination alone rules his Motions; and we do not ſee him as your Majeſty, an Idolator of his Perſon nor of his Preſervation: He is wont to ſay, That which God guards is well guarded. So, Sir, your Majeſty needs only give your conſent to the Undertakings, and we warrant the reſt.</p>
            <p>But, ſays his Majeſty, methinks <hi>Grandvall</hi> and <hi>Dumont</hi> are not ſufficient for ſo great a Deſign, but that there ſhould be yet ſome other ſort of Incendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries to animate and help them.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Barbeſieux,</hi> without doubt your Majeſty muſt needs think that King <hi>James</hi> is the Head of the Party, and that there are eight Actors more, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ready to do any thing, whoſe Names are theſe, <hi>Grandvall, Dumont, Lieſdal, Rebenac, Bidal, Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:175367:71"/> Paprel, Parcker, Chanlais</hi> and my ſelf; if your Majeſty accepts of the Propoſition, you will give great encouragement to the Undertaking.</p>
            <p>As to my ſelf, ſays his Majeſty, I am not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether my own Maſter; I have a Sovereign who reigns over my Will, and who has an Empire over me, much more abſolute than that I have over my Subjects, I mean, the Guides of my Conſcience, ſo that I dare not engage my ſelf in the Cabal, before I have conſulted my Prieſts.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſays <hi>Barbeſieux,</hi> the time preſſes and the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion is favourable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Barbeſieux,</hi> ſays his Majeſty, then let my Counſel of Conſcience be call'd, and I will conſult them thereupon. The Reverend Father <hi>la Chaize</hi> going out of the Chamber of Meditations appear'd with his triangular Cap, accompanied by Madam <hi>de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenon</hi> his Secretary, who carried under her Arm a great Book, in Folio, which had for Title, <hi>The Art to aſſaſſinate Kings.</hi> The Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> could not come, becauſe of the Diſpatches he had to write to <hi>Rome,</hi> the Poſt being juſt upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts departure.</p>
            <p>My Reverend Father, ſays his Majeſty, as you are a great Caſuiſt, and that you, like St. <hi>Peter,</hi> have full power to bind and unbind with me.</p>
            <p>What's the Buſineſs in hand, Sir, ſays the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father <hi>la Chaize,</hi> being impatient of knowing what he had to put to him?</p>
            <p>The Buſineſs in ſhort, ſays his Majeſty, is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit an execreable Attempt, and to know whether my Conſcience will not be charg'd with it, if I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to it.</p>
            <p>What is it then, ſays the Reverend Father?</p>
            <p>My good Father, ſays his Majeſty, <hi>Barbeſieux</hi> has juſt now propos'd to me a very ſhort way whereby I may, this Campaign, undoubtedly come to clap up a Peace, and there wants nothing but my conſent to have it ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cuted.</p>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:175367:71"/>
            <p>As what? as what? ſays the Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
            <p>Father, ſays his Majeſty, it has been reſolv'd to have the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> aſſaſſinated, as he who is the only Obſtacle to all my Deſigns: and as this Prince expoſes him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf very much, <hi>Grandvall</hi> and <hi>Dumont</hi> have engaged themſelves to deliver him alive or dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Opus plane Divinum!</hi> ſays the Reverend Father <hi>la Chaize.</hi> This Enterprize is all of God: <hi>Abſolvo te,</hi> Sir, I abſolve you. Thereupon, taking in hand the great Book that his Secretary Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> carried, he ſhewed to his Majeſty, by the Opinion of the moſt celebrated Authors of the Society, to wit, the Reverend Fathers <hi>Garnet, Suares, Eudemon, Parſons, Zimancka, Eſcobar, Sancher, Saiman, Fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> and a great number of others, That to take off a Heretick Prince from the Chriſtian World, by the Sword, Poiſon or otherwiſe, was a Work very acceptable to God, and the ſtrait way that led to Paradice.</p>
            <p>But 'tis time we put an end to a Conference which carries ſo much Horror with it, by the Deviſe of this great Prince, <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ni ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u qui mal y Penſe;</hi> and we will only ſay, That he hath us'd long ſince heartily to forgive all his Enemi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the Evils they would do him, and that he accounts it his Glory to pray to God for their R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pentance and their Converſion. But we may ſtill av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w, That it is a very baſe and odious Action f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>F ance,</hi> and of which <hi>Louis</hi> the Great, as Triumpha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, as Glorious and as great a Politician as he is, will never wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h himſelf clean, tho' he ſhould uſe all the Water of <hi>Verſailles</hi> or the Royal Canal: Meſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>urs <hi>de Boil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>au</hi> and <hi>de la Fontain,</hi> who are employed about writing this Hiſtory, ought by no means to forget marking this in great Characters, under <hi>Viro Immortali,</hi> and to ſpeak of it
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:175367:72"/> as one of the principal Events of his Reign. This will be the richeſt Flower of his Crown, and one of his faireſt Pictures, capable to draw admiration from all Ages to come. But I can't forbear ſaying here, by the way, That there have ſuch things been done in the Reign of this Monarch, which yet paſs, in the ſenſe of his Flatterers, for Actions Great and Heroick, which yet, to ſpeak ſincerely, are nothing leſs than ſuch; and if we ſhould put, as we ſay, the Hiſtory of his Life and of his Reign into a Crucible, there would be wrought a very ſurprizing change; for inſtead of Gold and the other fine glittering Gimcracks, wherewith thoſe Juglers uſe to cheat the deluded Multitude, there would come out nothing but ſo many Monſters, in different Shapes and Figures.</p>
            <p>It is to be fear'd, that of all theſe Prodigies of Glory and Grandeur, which at preſent ſeem to be the terror of his Subjects as well as of his Enemies, and as it were eſſential to his good Fortune, there would remain in the Furnace only a little Droſs and Smoak.</p>
            <p>But hold, let us not go too far, but turn for once the other ſide of the Medal, and take it on the faireſt ſide. We will ſpeak a little of his Glory, ſince he loves it ſo much, and it is his Favourite Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: We will own it true, that he is one of the greateſt Kings that the <hi>French</hi> Monarchy ever yet hath given us; that he is a very great Politician, very Wiſe in his Choice, and very Vigilant in the execution of a good Deſign; but then we muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this too, that this Prince would be a very great Hero, if he would but add to all theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Qualities, that one, of right knowing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, without ſuffering his Courtiers to offer him ſuch Incenſe as if he were another Divinity, and thereby commit that great overſight which <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:175367:72"/> the Great did formerly, when he exacted that they ſhould pay him <hi>Divine Honours.</hi> Let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member himſelf, that this was the firſt Forerunner of the fall of the Empire of that Prince, and of the great Deſigns he had conceiv'd of the Conqueſt of <hi>Aſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would adviſe him then, rather to rid himſelf of all thoſe <hi>Owls,</hi> who are always about his Sacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as Birds of an unhappy Omen, and who will leave him no more than the Devil formerly did our Saviour in the Wilderneſs, even till he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them to do all the miſchief they deſire.</p>
            <p>Here is the Source and Spring of all thoſe Evils and Calamities, which at preſent ſo cruelly afflict <hi>Europe.</hi> If this Prince would but once enter into his true Intereſts, and would change his Council, we might then ſee him the Wonder of the Univerſe; The imaginary Immortality with which they flatter him, would then be a real and ſolid one; which would procure him not only the Love of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but alſo the Reſpect and Veneration of the whole World.</p>
            <p>Here is enough for <hi>Louis</hi> the Great; let us go on to King <hi>James</hi> his good Friend.</p>
            <p>This Prince, as all the World knows, has long ſince bid adieu to Glory, and therefore it may be ſaid of him, That he is like an old Deſerter who has ſold all his Equipage, to go into the Service of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prince. Beſides, it is ſufficient that he is a Member of the Society, to carry in one hand the Sword and in the other the Flambeau. He ought to remember, That he was once fallen into the hands of his Competitor, who receiv'd him by Principles of Humanity and Chriſtianity, very different from his, who fought after nothing but Popery and Slavery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and if he could once in his Life imitate the leaſt of the Qualities of this great Prince,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:175367:73"/> whom he makes at preſent the Object of his Hatred, and whom he looks upon as his mortal Enemy, he would acquire many degrees of Glory and good Fortune, which he has not yet attained to, and 'tis to be feared ſcarce ever will. But God forgive him his Sins, and make him a good Chriſtian, if he has not been ſo yet. This may ſuffice to ſay of him; let us paſs on now to two other Gentlemen.</p>
            <p>Here is a fitting place to make their Panegyrick in a few words. But to ſpare them the Shame for having been the Inſtruments of ſo deteſtable an Undertaking, we will be content to make them only repaſs in review one after another, to the end they may be well known to the World.</p>
            <p>Let us begin then with Monſieur <hi>de Barbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieux,</hi> who preſents himſelf the firſt, his Sword in his Hand, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying, <hi>Kill, Kill;</hi> you muſt not wonder to ſee him ſo hot, for ſince the death of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs <hi>de Louvois,</hi> his Father, he fears nothing ſo much as a Reverſe of Fortune, and that <hi>Louis</hi> the Great ſhould one time or another take a fancy to ſerve him, as the Crow in the Fable, that is to ſay, to pull off his beſt Feathers, in taking from him his moſt profitable places, as he did formerly to the Children of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lbert.</hi> So Monſieur <hi>de Barbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieux,</hi> to keep himſelf in favour, has thought that he could not render a more ſignal pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce of Service to his Majeſty, than that of aſſaſſinating a Prince, who is at this da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bſtacle to all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of the King his Maſter, and the moſt glorious Prince in Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>Now let us make way for Monſieur <hi>de Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> and let him paſs by; he wears the Sword of the late Monſieu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>de Bouteville<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Father, that is to ſay, a dangerous Sword, and which gives Qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter to no Body; methinks I hear him ſay, what <hi>Rodrigus</hi> ſaid to the Earl, in the Play of <hi>Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <q>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:175367:73"/>
                  <l>That Arder which I carry in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Eyes,</l>
                  <l>Do you know it is his Blood? do you know it?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>So, it is not the firſt of his Wickedneſſes his hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing attempted the Life of King <hi>William;</hi> and we may ſay of him without a Compliment, That his Sins are become a habit to him, and he is now too much advanced in years ever to have any hopes that he will correct himſelf.</p>
            <p>But to give yet a j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſter I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea of what he can do, we will add here, to ſatisfie the Curious, the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Agreement which he formerly made with the Devil, juſt as we find them in the Original, which have been communicated to us, to wit,
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>That he gave himſelf wholly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o him, with Promiſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>That he would never ſpeak of God, and that he would n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ver go to Maſs.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>That he ſhould be without Pity and Mercy.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>On the other ſide the Devil engag'd himſelf,
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>To favour him in all his Deſigns.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>To make him win all the Battles he ſhould fight.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>To keep him always in the Love and Favour of his King.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IV. <hi>To cauſe him to have, when he would, all manner of Favours of the faireſt Ladies.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>V. <hi>To make h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m Invulnerable.</hi> And,</item>
                  <item>VI. <hi>That he ſhould live to the Age of Seventy Five Years.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But you will ſay, where was Monſieur <hi>de Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> before the Battle of <hi>Flerus,</hi> which made him live again, and drew him, as we ſay, from the Grave of Silence and Forgetfulneſs, where he had been ſhut
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:175367:74"/> up ſince the Wars of <hi>Holland?</hi> Nothing was leſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd, than that he was yet in the World; and the Opinions were ſo divided th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reupon, that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knew not what to believe. Some th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ught him in <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tland</hi> at the Head of the <hi>Highla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> Rebels; others believ'd him with a Turbet on in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army, and turn'd into a Grand Vizier; and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uly one would have judg'd that the little Genius t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey had, the good Fortune and Progreſs which follow'd the firſt Campaign that the Infidels made in <hi>Hungary,</hi> was but an effect of his <hi>Negromancy:</hi> it was fear'd alſo, that he had already taught them the greateſt Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Art and Knowledge.</p>
            <p>But others better inſtructed in the Hiſtory of his Life, and wiſer in the Affairs of the times, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly believ'd, That the Court of <hi>Fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce,</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather the Council of the King had thought fit to deliver him to the mercy of Juſtice, to make him an Example, as they had don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inviliiers,</hi> as well to appeaſe the People and the Clergy, as to ſatisfie his Majeſty's Council of Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cience.</p>
            <p>The Reverend Father <hi>la Chaize</hi> dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar'd himſelf a Party againſt him, and fought his death, with as much fierceneſs, as one of the ing's Attornies doth that of a Criminal for High Treaſon. So they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan already to ſacrifice him, and all the World thought him juſt going to fini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h his days upon a Scaffold, with as much Infamy as his unhappy Father had done before him.</p>
            <p>The Crime then which he was accus'd of had ſomething in it the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt agg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ava<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, the moſt crying and the moſt enormous in the World, ſince they had join'd Poiſon to Magick. Beſides, the death of the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or Count <hi>de S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſſons,</hi> with which he was charg'd, cryed aloud to Heaven for Vengeance. Others believ'd that the King, as angry as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſeem'd to be againſt him, having made ſome Reflections
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:175367:74"/> on the ſervices, that this General had formerly done him in his former Wars, was at laſt pleaſed to change his ſentence of Death into that of Baniſhment, or perpetual Impriſonment. There was alſo a ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance that this laſt way of puniſhment was moſt likely to prevail with him, that which his Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors and his J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dges had choſe, and which they puſh'd on to the laſt, according to the utmoſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of Law and practice.</p>
            <p>Be it as it will, it is certain, and it is the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe who are perfectly acquainted with his Hiſtory, as having always beeen near his Perſon in the greateſt time of his diſgrace; and who have very wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ingly Communicated to us the Memorials which are reported in this ſmall Treatiſe. It is, I ſay, certain, that Monſieur the Marques <hi>de Louvois</hi> took his buſineſs ſo ſtrongly to Heart, that we may ſay, Monſieur <hi>de Luxemburgh</hi> doth not only owe him his Liberty, but alſo his Life, as well as the new favours which his Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſty Honours him with at preſent, by the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmand of his Armies, which he e'en truſts him with.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>de Louvois,</hi> ſeeing then that his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs was done, and that the poor Duke was irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably loſt; as he was a wiſe Miniſter, and pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating what might hereafter happen, he thought that <hi>France</hi> might yet have occaſion of him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that all the old Generals that were of any Eſteem, and Reputation, began to fail them; and that the Duke of <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> as being the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, was the only one who remain'd; truly Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Turenne,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> and in the laſt place the Duke of <hi>Schomberg</hi> had been raviſhed from the King, thoſe by Death, and this by the diſorders of Religion; ſo very judiciouſly reflecting that the loſs the King lately had of theſe three Captains, was irreparable, and that beſides <hi>France</hi>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:175367:75"/> was juſt a going into ſuch a condition in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, that ſhe ſtands in need of all Aſſiſtances and Inſtruments, he was throughly convinced that all imaginable Obſtacles ought to be remov'd to preſerve him.</p>
            <p>He went then to find out his Majeſty, and told him, Sir, this is not all; your Majeſty ſees your ſelf at the very point of having all <hi>Europe</hi> upon your hands, and the War which is a going to be kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, will perhaps be the bloodieſt that <hi>France</hi> ever yet felt, not only in this Reign, but thoſe that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded; and as your Majeſty will have many Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to fight with, ſo you will be obliged to have ſeveral Armies. But, Sir, that which cauſes not the leaſt of my diſturbances, is, to ſee that you have not one General left, who has underſtanding enough, and is capable to Command: It is true, you have yet Lieutenant Genera's enough; But for a General in Chief, who is a Man of Conduct, who has experience and cunning, and has been in Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles whether he has won or loſt; it is no matter, which of them, for experience makes them Maſters, I know no Body belongs to your Majeſty except <hi>Luxemburgh.</hi> He is the only one who in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeems fit to become a great Captain, if he is not ſo already, and conſequently in a condition to do you great ſervice. I adviſe then your Majeſty to paſs over all his faults of which he is accus'd, to ſatisfie, nevertheleſs as much as you, can your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Conſcience, in leaving the Criminal at the <hi>Baſtile,</hi> and cauſing his Tryal under-hand to be delay'd, which will flatter the hopes of his Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and at the ſame time appeaſe the moſt inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate againſt him, who not being able to divine the true cauſe, will tire themſelves with talking about it; and your Majeſty will preſerve thereby a Subject, who may be ſerviceable to you in buſineſs when it ſhall be a fit time.</p>
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:175367:75"/>
            <p>After this Diſcourſe Monſieur <hi>de Louvois,</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that his Majeſty appear'd half ſhaken, thought that Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> would be of great help to him, to puſh on the buſineſs effectually. He went then to ſpeak with he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and repreſented to her as he had done to the King, the neceſſity there was to ſave this General which was loſt without recovery, if he ſhould be left fifteen days more in the hands of his Judges, who would by all extremity m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke him an Example. He added that there was no time to be loſt, &amp; that <hi>France</hi> would one day owe him great Obligations, if ſhe would ſave a Subject, who was ſo dear and ſo neceſſary for her, which beſides the great ſervices he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready render'd the Crown, gave yet great hopes for the future, That he was the only one left, of ſo many brave Captains, who had Commanded in the former Wars, and who having ſerv'd under <hi>Turenne</hi> and <hi>Conde,</hi> had learnt by theſe great Men many fine qualities neceſſary for the Government and Conduct of an Army, which will not be found in the Perſon of another General.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> who is a true Siren near the King, and who ſees her ſelf Miſtreſs of the Heart and Will of this Monarch, by her flattering Amours, was ſo lively perſwaded by the Diſcourſe of Monſieur <hi>de Lovois,</hi> that ſhe immediately eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the cauſe, and the intereſt of Monſieur <hi>de Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emburgh,</hi> and promis'd the Marquis <hi>de Louvois</hi> to ſpeak to the King the very firſt viſit ſhe made, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding withal, that ſhe did not doubt but ſhe ſhould obtain the pardon of this unhappy Man, and draw him out of his diſgrace, unleſs that the Inſtances and the Intrigues of Father <hi>La Chaize,</hi> and of the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> ſhould prevail over hers; that for him who was the chief of the Clergy of <hi>France,</hi> ſhe had the means in her Hands to appeaſe him, but that Father <hi>La Chaize,</hi> would give her a great deal more trouble, becauſe this good Father was
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:175367:76"/> an Enemy to be fear'd, and it was by no means good to have him a party againſt one; that ſhe would endeavour nevertheleſs to perſwade both the one, and the other, which ſhe alſo did, and Monſieur <hi>de Luxemburgh</hi> was no leſs beholding for his liberty to Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> than to Monſieur <hi>de Louvois,</hi> ſince they equally labour'd for his preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The King having been thus prepoſſeſs'd, and the Storm rais'd againſt him entirely appeas'd, the Duke began to hope in Priſon to have ſome more Liberty, and to taſt ſome comfort. He was no more kept ſo cloſe up, and his Guards began to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more negligent in obſerving him; He was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs kept in the Baſtille a long time af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erwards, by which the Court thought to become Guiltleſs in the Eyes of the World, to the end it might not ſeem altogether a Connivance, and an Authorizing of the Crime by granting liberty to a Criminal, whom all the Laws condemn'd to death. This was done only to diſpoſe by degrees the People and his Inquiſitors, to receive with leſs noiſe the news of his Releaſe. The time being then come that <hi>France</hi> had occaſion for him, as the Marqueſs <hi>de Louvois</hi> had foretold; and the King having expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienc'd the firſt Campaign, which was that of 1689. that his Armies were ill govern'd, and that they did not Act conformab y to his intention, and as he had well enough laid the Scheam; that if on the other ſide his Arms had not had ſucceſs that year, it was not for want of Forces, and being ſeconded and ſupported by great Armies, but rather the fault of the General, who was neither undertaking enough, nor cunning enough. His Majeſty ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving caus'd the Duke of <hi>Luemburgh,</hi> to be call'd would in granting him grace and pardon take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion from thence to engage him by new favours
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:175367:76"/> to be more mindful than ever of his Intereſts; and make that his acknowledment, ſhould be a potent inducement to this General, to excel above all what he had done well and glorious for the ſervice of his Prince, in the former Wars, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in that of <hi>Holland,</hi> where he had ſignaliz'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by his Cruelties. And as the matter in hand, was to give him the Command of the Army in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> becauſe it was there where he had the beſt ſucceeded, if we except the Battle of St. <hi>Denis,</hi> the King wiſely thought that he would not fail to make himſelf quickly talk'd of, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to feel new marks of his inhumanity, which <hi>France</hi> wanted above all things to oblige yet tottering Fortune to declare her ſelf for her Arms.</p>
            <p>It was reſolv'd upon, utterly to ruin the reſt of <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> to the end that he might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Maſter of them with more eaſe, thereby to force the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to hearken to new propoſitions of Peace, which is the aim of his Majeſty, and the deſign of the Court.</p>
            <p>Experience ſhews us then at this day, that the Marqueſs <hi>de Lovois</hi> was in the right. For Monſieur <hi>de Luxemburgh</hi> ſtrives on his ſide fully to anſwer all the expectations of his Benefactor, and the hopes he had conceiv'd of him, by the ſignal Services which he renders his Majeſty, not only in helping him to ſupport the heavy burden of the preſent War; but alſo in diſcovering to him a ſhort and abridg'd way to come quickly to a glorious Peace; and as he is a Man that abounds in malice, and knows ſufficiently what is Good and Evil, yet he ſtrives to forget that little of Humanity, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity which is left him, &amp; goes on in a full Career, with his Sword in his Hand, into that Cabal, which ſeeks how to find out Kings, and then to aſſaſſinate them. Here is enough for Monſieur <hi>de Luxemburgh,</hi>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:175367:77"/> let us finiſh his Chapter, and bid him adieu for altogether, with putting him in mind that 'tis high time for him to ſet about his Converſion, unleſs he will dye as he has liv'd.</p>
            <p>Let us go on to Monſieur <hi>de Chanlais,</hi> Fourth Actor of this Cabal, he keeps himſelf behind the Hangings, feigning as if he had hid himſelf. He does like thoſe that throw a Stone, and hide their Arm. But methinks he would do better to acquit himſelf well, of the Charge which he poſſeſs in the Army, that would be more honourable, and more glorious for him, than to make here the ſorrowful Figure of the <hi>Valet</hi> of a Hangman, in lending his hand to the Aſſaſſinates.</p>
            <p>Behold Monſieur <hi>Rabenac</hi> who walks a pace, let us ſee what he will have to ſay to juſtifie himſelf for having had alſo a part in ſo black of an Action. He will not fail to ſay, that the overgreat Zeal he had for the Intereſts of the King his Maſter did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage him therein.</p>
            <p>What ſlavery is this, That a Miniſter ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage to commit a deteſtable Crime before God and Men, for nothing but to pleaſe his Prince! But it may be he will perform his Repentance, whilſt he is at <hi>Rome,</hi> and ask pardon of God and of the Holy Father for ſo great a Sin.</p>
            <p>For Meſſieurs <hi>Bidal</hi> and <hi>Paparal,</hi> we will put them together to make the balance even, becauſe they are truly of the ſame Metal and the ſame Weight. And if for curioſity one ſhould weigh their malice, I do not believe they would either of them want many Scruples to make the Scale even. So it is no very ſtrange thing, that they have plaid the ſame part in this Tragedy. Good God then have mercy on them.</p>
            <p>As to Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Offi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, we
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:175367:78"/> may juſtly ſay he follow'd the Councils of his Prince King <hi>James,</hi> who engag'd him to the Party by fair promiſes of advancing his Fortunes; and we may ſay of him, that the Man was not better than the Maſter; ſo let God give him Peace as the reſt.</p>
            <p>But hold, here is one would fain ſlip by, what ſhall we ſay of him? he ſeems as if he were afraid of being known. He appears to me the more to be fear'd, therefore let us have a care of him, and let him go by quickly. It ſeems he is not wholly well pleaſed; for we dont any longer ſee that ſmiling Countenance which he uſed to ſhew when he was at the <hi>Hague</hi> as he went out in a Coach. But I am impatient to know him, therefore through Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity let us pull off his Mask: Ho, ho, it is Monſieur <hi>Moreau.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſpare a great deal of confuſion, let us content our ſelves with making him the Complement that <hi>Seneca</hi> in his Tragedies caus'd to be made to <hi>Jaſon</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Medea, purga Regnum, &amp; veneficas tecum aufer herbas,</hi> that he may be gone as ſoon as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and carry with him all the evil he would have done to the State, and that he may come back no more.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>Grandval, Dumont</hi> and <hi>Leefdal,</hi> the laſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of this Tragick Scene, I do not pretend to ſpeak one word of them, becauſe I look upon them, as the executioners of the Orders of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Tribunal, which made them Act; and that's ſufficient for their Apology.</p>
            <p>But we muſt not forget here the Encomiums of Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> who has made no ſcruple neither to fowl her Fair White Hands in the Plot of an Aſſaſſinate. She is at leaſt as much to be fear'd as the Goddeſs of <hi>Diſcord</hi> formerly was at the Feaſts of the Marriage of <hi>Peleus,</hi> and would not
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:175367:79"/> fail to revenge her ſelf in a much more cruel man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than this Important and Angry Goddeſs did. It is alſo to be fear'd, that ſhe would throw into the Aſſembly, either ſome Carcaſſes or ſome Bombs, inſtead of Golden Apples. Let us then prevent her Jealouſie and her Fury; for a Woman in Wrath is dangerous. Let us give her rather Incenſe to appeaſe her, and ſay in her praiſe, that ſhe is Virtuous, Zealous, and Active as may be; that ſhe ſtrives alſo to render great Services to the <hi>French</hi> Monarchy; and that when ever we come to a Peace ſhe will have no leſs Contributed to it, by her Cares, than the Arms of her Monarch. But let us ſay alſo at the ſame time, that ſhe gives a very bad example to the Ladies of the Abby of St. <hi>Cyr,</hi> of which ſhe is Superiour, and that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Council of Conſcience, will never juſtifie her before God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the Crime ſhe has committed, in giving her advice to ſo horrible an attempt. I adviſe her then to diſpoſe of her ſelf early, to go make her Repentance in the Convent of Penitents by the Example of thoſe that have gone before her. Here is enough for her, let us go on.</p>
            <p>As for the Reverend Father <hi>La Chaize.</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I ſee him appear, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olding in one hand the Sword, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h which the great St. <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> was about to kill the <hi>Moor</hi> (in going his Voyage to <hi>Spain</hi>) who would maintain to him that the bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> was no Virgin af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Conception.</p>
            <p>Methinks alſo, in the other Hand he carries a Book in Folio, which has for Title, <hi>The Art to aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſinate Kings and Princes.</hi> But let us not enter into a Diſpute with him, for fear he ſhould be oblig'd to borrow all the Eloquence of Father <hi>Bourdalou</hi> to juſtifie himſelf. To raiſe yet again the Glory of all theſe Tragical Actors, we may join here to
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:175367:79"/> their Cabal, the Il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſtrious <hi>James Clement, Barriere, Chaſtel, Ravaillac, John Iuvr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gni, Venero, Balthuzar Gerard, Peter Paine, Parri</hi> and a great many more of them, as we may find by the Rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt of <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neira</hi> the Jeſuit, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ch.</hi> 3. who have attempted the Lives of the Kings, <hi>Henry</hi> the Third and <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, of Great <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> his Son Prince <hi>Maurice,</hi> and of Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is no aſtoniſhing thing that we ſee at this day all the Court of <hi>France,</hi> and ſo many brave Lords who have formerly witneſſed their having had a Horror for ſo deteſtablea Doctrine, to be never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs blindly engaged in ſuch a Cabal, after having cruelly underwrit to the death of the greateſt Prince of <hi>Europe.</hi> After this Stroke, I ſay, may we not ſay, That the whole Monarchy is at this day govern'd by Jeſuits; and that inſtead of one <hi>Louis</hi> the Fourteenth, we ſee one Father <hi>la Chaize</hi> reigning and ſitting upon the Throne of the <hi>French,</hi> giving his Orders, and making all his Tragical and Bloody Actors to perform their parts.</p>
            <p>And as the Soul of <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> is an Active Soul, and by conſequence, the moſt conformable to the Soul of this Reverend Father, ſo has he been cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to be at the Head of theſe Aſſaſſinates the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to command them, and to add yet this Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to the Hiſtory of his Life, as the laſt Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of it.</p>
            <p>But let us come to our purpoſe, and confeſs, That all theſe Proceedings are made by <hi>France,</hi> to come quickly to her end, which is an advantagious Peace. Let us alſo add, for Concl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſion, That <hi>Louis</hi> the Great, often miſtakes himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Execution of his vaſt Deſigns; ſince of all the Reſolutions he had taken for this Campaign, Experience has ſhewn us that he was out in his Account<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> about the Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:175367:80"/> Re-eſtabliſhment of King <hi>James,</hi> about the Engagement at Sea, about the Entry of the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> into <hi>Dauphine,</hi> and about the aſſaſſinating of King <hi>William.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, he made himſelf Maſter of <hi>Namur,</hi> which was one of the four great Undertakings that was the object of his Ambition. But then we may alſo own, that this Triumph has been ſufficiently counterbalanc'd by the ruin of his Fleet, and of the Deſigns of King <hi>James,</hi> which are all blown into the Air, by the glorious Irruption of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who has put his Country under Contribution; and, laſtly, by the Shame and Infamy which will always attend the Baſeneſs of having attempted on the Life of ſo great a Prince. And here are the Events which have flatter'd this Monarch into the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a Campaign, but which nevertheleſs have not anſwer'd the great hopes he had conceiv'd. Let us ſee, at preſent, what he will undertake anew, and if his Projects will have the ſame Succeſs the next Campaign: Let us wait for him boldly, and make him ſee that our People are not ſo weary of the War as his Subjects; and that if he will come to a glorious Peace, with which he flatters himſelf, and ſeeks after with eagerneſs, he muſt, at the leaſt, ſurrender up all his Conqueſts.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:175367:80"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175367:81"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175367:81"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
